<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe methode or way teachinge all sortes of Christian people, how to serue God in a moste perfect manner written first in Spanishe, by a religious man, named Alphonso ; and reduced owte of Latin into English in manner of a dialogue for the easier vnderstanding and capacities of the simpler sorte, by I.M.</title>
            <author>Alonso, de Madrid.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 535.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22095541</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22095541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1762:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe methode or way teachinge all sortes of Christian people, how to serue God in a moste perfect manner written first in Spanishe, by a religious man, named Alphonso ; and reduced owte of Latin into English in manner of a dialogue for the easier vnderstanding and capacities of the simpler sorte, by I.M.</title>
                  <author>Alonso, de Madrid.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[19], 73 [i.e. 145], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.M. is probably John Mitchell or Michel, a Carthusian monk at Bruges--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints; date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Secretly printed in England, between 1602 and 1605--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on verso only.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁸ L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Catholic authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BREEFE METHODE OR WAY Teachinge all ſortes of Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, how to ſerue God in a moſte perfect manner. Written firſt in Spaniſhe, by a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man, named <hi>Alphonſo.</hi> And reduced owte of Latin into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh in manner of a Dialogue for the eaſier vnderſtanding and capacities of the ſimpler ſorte.</p>
            <p>By I. M.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipfull, &amp; vertuous Cathol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck Lady, the La. M. C.</head>
            <p>ALbeit mankinde, by the ſtinge of originall ſinne, be deadlye wounded in body &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule, as ſpoyled of immortali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e &amp; all diuine graces, broughte into a wofull ſtate of all miſeries, &amp; naturallye inclyned to doe euill, to the greater encreaſe of his owne damnation: yet the grace &amp; mercy of God, haith not altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned nor forſaken vs, but (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any our good deſert) haith lefte vs in this exile &amp; vale of woes, diuers helpes, remedies, &amp; meanes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may attayne to his graceous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure agayne, &amp; (after this tranſitorie lyfe) be aduaunced to high glorie and the eternall ioyes in heauen. Theſe meanes are his holy graces &amp; vertues by which we may be moued &amp; made able to ſerue him, &amp; to conforme our ſelues to his will in all thinges. Oure perfect ſanctity &amp; frendſhipp with god ſtandeth in this pointe, that we be of
<pb facs="tcp:25031:2"/>ſame ſpirit with him, in euery thing we doe. And though he be a moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceous &amp; bountifull Lorde, &amp; excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly deſireous of our eternall happy eſtate: And haith moreouer abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouyded whatſoeuer may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or conuenient for our welfare: yea &amp; through the exceſſe of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine loue, haith lefte nothing vndone that might helpe or doe vs good: yet haith he lefte it in our owne choyce, &amp; free libertie, whether we will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and vſe his graces, endeuour to gett perfect holines, &amp; ſerue him as he deſyreth for our good, or noe. Great ruyne and deſtruction of all good, is made in oure ſoules by ſinne, but it is in our owne power to repayre again this loſſe &amp; calamitie, and to obtayne perfect holines, which we may doe, if (cooperating with goddes grace) we ſuffer our ſelues to be moued in all our actions onely by goddes holy ſpirit &amp; will, as S. Paule ſaithe his children to be.</p>
            <p>To inſtruct this, many deuout bokes &amp; Treatiſes haue bene writen by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:25031:3"/>&amp; holy men in all ages, teaching what we ought to doe, diſcourſing at large of the natures of all vertues &amp; vyces, &amp; yelding ſufficient matter for all ſorts of holy Meditations touching the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, goodnes, &amp; other perfections of god: Touching heauen, hell, Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, death, ſinne, vertue, and the reſt: Perſwading to good lyfe &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyinge from euill: All commodious woorkes &amp; commendable trauells of good men. But amonge them all I neuer founde hitherto any comparable to a litle booke, deuulged by a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man named <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> in the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh tonge. In which goulden Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, he geueth vs an exacte &amp; perfect way, how we may repayre againe the ruine &amp; wofull ſtate of our ſoules, by ſinn: &amp; by rightly ſeruinge God, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the perfection of true holines &amp; loue of him. This Author leauethe the large &amp; goodly diſcourſes of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues &amp; vyces, their reaſons, examples, perſwaſions, &amp; allpoynts of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (as all beinge ſufficientlye Taughte and handled, by others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable
<pb facs="tcp:25031:3"/>and to be founde euery where,) and breefely touchinge the ende for which God created and placed vs on earthe, what bounde &amp; dutie we haue of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge him: what abiection &amp; miſerie our ſoules &amp; bodies are brought vnto by ſinne: He ſheweth a breefe, yet a moſt exacte way and manner, how by the inſtrumentes and powers of oure ſoule, namely our vnderſtandinge and free will, helped by godds grace, we may put in practiſe and execution, to his moſt holy honour, and our owne greateſt profitt, whatſoeuer is taughte &amp; conteyned in other bookes, how we may repayre our ſtate againe, caſte of all wicked cuſtomes, expell all vitious habitts, enryche &amp; bewtify oure ſelues with all vertues, make all our woorks moſt preceous, acceptable, &amp; meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, in goddes ſight, becom holy chaunge our ſelues owt of poore, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; abiect perſons: into moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; diuine creatures: And finally be vnited to God in moſt perfect man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of frendſhipp &amp; loue.</p>
            <p>This preceous Iewell, I ſende you,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:4"/>as a token of my good affection, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes your ſpirituall welfare, which I haue tranſlated owt of latin, not yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding woord for woord, but (cullinge owt the principall poyntes &amp; pithe of euery Chapter) haue reduced it into the forme of a Dyalogue, thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge it more eaſye &amp; playne, for the capacities of the ſimpler ſorte, whom alſo I wiſh, may take commodity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as I aſſure my ſelfe, your La. and euery one may doe, that reade &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently practiſe, what is taught there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: without which practiſe, all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is vnprofitable and vayne. It is not writen for vitious perſons, ſuche as delight to lyue &amp; wallow in ſinne, without regarde of God or their own ſoules health, for theſe will take noe benefite hereof, but the Author haith prepared &amp; directed this woorke, for the great good of vertuous ſoules who are reſolued to ſerue God: &amp; ſtanding in battell againſt the worlde, the fleſh &amp; the deuill, haue a ſincere defyre, to liue well &amp; woorke their owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This good euery one that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe
<pb facs="tcp:25031:4"/>it, may reape: that knowinge thereby their owne poore &amp; imperfect ſtate, &amp; behoulding how farr of they are from that degree of perfection they ſhould &amp; might arryue vnto; They may abaſe them ſelues in their owne conceyte, carry an humble mynde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heauen &amp; earthe, of their owne imperfections &amp; vnworthines, which is a good ſtepp to further vertue: and be moued now &amp; then, to work ſom particuler acts after the manner hereof which aſſuredly will be moſt pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to God, &amp; moſt meritorious to their own ſoules aboue all other woorkes they ſhall doe.</p>
            <p>Now in your afflicted ſtate where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are toſſed too and froe daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly, by the enemies of godds ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly churche, for your conſtancy in the catholick Faith: Alphonſo will teache you how to fraught your ſhipp, with all ſortes of vertues, more preceous then the Indian Treaſures, that you may come well loaden to the porte, when your Lord ſhall ende your voyage.</p>
            <p>How alſo to endure patiently, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge
<pb facs="tcp:25031:5"/>&amp; furious ſtormes of Godds e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And how finally to keepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſale, and an humble conceite of your ſelues in all the good you doe, &amp; to referr all the honour &amp; prayſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto God the owner &amp; geuer of all good giftes. For it is a moſt certaine way to loſſe &amp; ſhipp-wracke of all, to impute any good to your ſelfe, or to carry a high conceit of your owne well doinge.</p>
            <p>Many vertuouſly diſpoſed ſoules, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light greatly in varietie &amp; chaunge of their ſpirituall Exerciſes, &amp; imbrace with greate affection euery noueltye, ſeking to know many wayes to ſerue God: &amp; euer think that to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the beſt, which is ſtraunge and vnknown to them, &amp; that which they throughly know and haue vſed, they either loath or litle eſteme, ſuch is the inconſtancye of our nature. But this new-fangled mutabilitye, exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hindreth all ſpirituall good and the progreſſe in all vertue. And with out compariſon better it were diligently to kepe &amp; practiſe one (thoughe it be a
<pb facs="tcp:25031:5"/>meaner) then to be either negligente in the beſt, or to be allwayes incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly flitting from one to an other: for ſo ſhould a man neither goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, nor grow perfect in any.</p>
            <p>Be familiar therefore &amp; ſtay youre ſelfe with Alphonſo (good Madam) for ſo ſhall you profitt greatly. And beware you be not content with the vertue you haue allready gotten: For our Lorde &amp; God was made man, &amp; vouchſaifed to dye, for to aduaunce vs to a higher &amp; perfect ſtate of holines in this lyfe: For this ſame ende alſo he would that Angells ſhoulde mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto vs: And finallye for the ſame ende he haith g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen vs the vſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; earth with all his creatures in them. Remember me I beſeche you in your deuotions. And thus I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt you to God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſeruant in our Lord. I. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OF The Author Alphonſo.</head>
            <p>SAinct <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the order &amp; manner how to woorke, greatly troubleth the qualitie of our meritt. Neither is it to be thought (as the ſame Author affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) that we haue full knowledge of a thinge which we know we ought to doe, vnleſſe we know withall the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of proceedinge in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Whereupon it is manifeſt, that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth verie litle, if one know what is writen for ſeruing God, &amp; be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in what manner and order it is to be done. And albeit arte &amp; knowledge of euery good thinge, floweth from God the ſupremeſt artificer, &amp; many be illuminated by his goodnes, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented with benedictions of delighte &amp; ſweetenes: yet for all that we muſt not omitt to doe what is in vs, to ſeke (as we are bounde) his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; will, &amp; other thinges which be neceſſary for doinge perfectly what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is pleaſing vnto him. For which
<pb facs="tcp:25031:6"/>purpoſe the breefe forme &amp; Methode which here we ſett downe, will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that we may know &amp; woorke thoſe greate thinges, which the holy ſcriptures teach vs. The which to doe it is noe leſſe needefull that ſome arte be ſought owte, then for doinge any other thinge which we couert rightly to know or woorke. To fynde owte this arte, the holye Doctoures haue ſpente much tyme, &amp; haue lefte it wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at large in diuers volumes: of all which, we will gather a breefe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſomme. But this ſhort work being chiefly ordeyned for the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſes of the ſoule: it will ſeme ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes verye obſcure to them which haue not bene exercyſed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; operations of the powers of their ſoule. Yet we ſhall ſhewe after a while in the proſecution of the book this Methode to be ſo farre from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie, that it bringeth greate lighte to all other bookes of lyke argument.</p>
            <p>Neither lett any thinke it ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or vayne, that we geue Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes whereby we may be helped to
<pb facs="tcp:25031:7"/>ſerue God, when as all the Scripture witneſſith ſuch to be neceſſary. And S.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, that we are helpers or coadiutors of God: but he either hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not rightly, or not ſufficientlye, that helpeth not as much as he can &amp; oughte. Neither is it any other thing in vs that we helpe God, then that we moue our ſoule in all our workes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcripte rule of this preſent arte, as ſacred diuinitie at large declareth.</p>
            <p>The Philoſopher in his Metaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks affirmeth, that mankinde liue the by arte: in which place he ſemeth by this propertie to diſtinguiſh man from vnreaſonable creatures, for that all theſe are moued onely by naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct without arte: but man is ruled by arte &amp; reaſon: Wherefore he may be ſaid to ſerue God as it we are onely by naturall inſtinct, lyke to creatures voyde of reaſon, that is moued to ſerue him that way, by which he fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth greateſt conſolation &amp; ſweetenes without regardinge by his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge &amp; reaſon, whether there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:25031:7"/>other manner, wherby he may be able, to ſerue God more excellently.</p>
            <p>Moreouer there is noe cauſe, why any ſhould alledge the vnction of the holy Ghoſt, to teach vs in all things, &amp; therfore any art or Methode where by we may learne to ſerue God, is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>needeles: which ſayinge is true, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſinge that we our ſelues alſo be his coadiutors or helpers, endeuoringe to know &amp; woorke, as we are taughte in the ſacred ſcriptures, &amp; in this arte which we are to geue. For the vncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy ghoſt, teachethe not them that are vnwillinge to learne, nor them that are idle, or make reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Furthermore leſte the ſweete yoke of our Lorde ſeme heauye to any, let vs conſider that it is not a thing to be merueled at, if ſome dayes are to be ſpent, for getting ſo highe knowledg &amp; wiſdom, as is heare conteyned and taught in this arte. For if in learninge Grammer or Logick (artes farr infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to this) one conſume &amp; ſpende 3 or 4 yeares, yea all his lyfo, if he
<pb facs="tcp:25031:8"/>will be perfecte in any of them: how much better is our lyfe beſtowed (yea if it be wholly ſpente therein) for the perfect learning of this arte moſt high &amp; diuine of all other artes, which our ſupreame maiſter Ieſus Chriſte, came to teach vs, with his ſo great toile &amp; payne.</p>
            <p>Moreover, he that beginnethe to learne this arte, muſt conſider, that it will happen to him, as it is wonte to happen to infantes, who hauinge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſoules, yet want the vſe of reaſon: and hauing in their bodyes handes &amp; fecte, yet can not goe or worke: but when they once begin to waxe and to moue their limmes, they goe, yet with great difficultie, &amp; with fallinge now &amp; then: but growing elder, &amp; vſinge daily Exercyſe, they goe ſo freelye, that they can runne at their pleaſures.</p>
            <p>The ſame hapneth in theſe Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whyles one deſyrethe purelye to ſerue god aſter this Methode: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit our ſoules be perfect &amp; intyere, yet ſo mightely are we bounde &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed &amp; without ſtrength to mooue
<pb facs="tcp:25031:8"/>our ſelues in the perfecte way manifeſted in the holy goſpell, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in this arte which we ſett owte, that at the firſte, we can not walke or goe at all, or if we be moued or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this, it is with ſuch difficultie, that our goinge is well neare nothing. Yet notwithſtanding let vs manfullye endeuour to doe what is here preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſo well as we can: for whiles we ſhall ſcarſe dare, to hope to gett the perfection taught vs, we ſhall by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe yea ſo runne by theſe high pathes that it may be ſaid truly, our motions to be rather the motions of an Angell flying, then of a man walking on earth.</p>
            <p>None oughte to pretende any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe why he ſerueth not God after the manner we haue here ſett downe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting him ſelf with the litterall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of ſom religious rule, or the commaundements of God, as ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente to ſaluation. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, Goddes will is that we be holy and perfect. Seinge therefore riches allready gotten, do not ſuffyce nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente the louers of the world, but all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:25031:9"/>they wiſhe &amp; couet more, yea often contrary to Goddes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Neither in lyke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner ought we to be contente with theſe ſpirituall riches we haue allreadie: but labour to increaſe them dailye, &amp; augmente the rewarde we expecte, ſeinge God doth vehemently deſyre that we ſo do. But if our appetite couet not this, for the profitt we may gert thereby, at the leaſt it ſhoulde extende it ſelfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre it, becauſe we know it to be gods will that we be magnifyed &amp; enrych<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all thinges, as the children of ſo eternall &amp; glorious a Father in heauen, who admoniſheth vs ſaying, <hi>Be you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe I your Lorde god &amp; Father am holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This booke may be intituled, <hi>The Way, Arte, or Methode, of fitly ſeruing God:</hi> which may be deuyded into three partes. The firſt conteyneth certaine vniuerſall documents, inſtructions, or rules, whereby we may be directed in all our actions. The ſeconde part co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth certaine particuler Exercyſes, in which the ſeruant of God muſte be
<pb facs="tcp:25031:9"/>exercyſed, that he may repaire the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and corruption which ſinne haithe brought into his ſoule.</p>
            <p>The Third part treateth of the loue of god, and thoſe thinges which he commaundeth to be loued, in which loue conſiſtethe the fulfillinge of the Law, and of all our good. And let him marke that ſhall reade this, how much labour &amp; diligence he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that deſyreth to be conninge and furniſhed in ſome prophane arte, and how meete it is, that more diligence be vſed in this affayre.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations therfore had &amp; chefely relying vpon the aſſiſtance of our ſupreme maiſter Ieſus Chriſt, our eternall God and Lorde, we will begin the foreſaid arte &amp; Method.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:10"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:10"/>
               <head>THE FIRST CHAPTER. HOW THE PILGRIM and the Ermit mett, &amp; of their conference.</head>
               <p>IN <hi>Mantua,</hi> there once dwelled a Knight called <hi>Probus,</hi> who for his valour, wiſdom, &amp; other vertues, was much renowmed in his countrye, &amp; of all ſtates very dearely beloued. He was of a moſt deuout &amp; religious diſpoſition, ſtudying more to ſerue &amp; pleaſe the omnipotent king of heauen, then the worlde or any earthly prince.</p>
               <p>About the ſolemne feaff of Eaſter, he woulde goe on pilgrimage, to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitt <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> &amp; other deuoute places of the holy lande. And as he traueled through a deſerte in <hi>Siria,</hi> he miſſed his way &amp; was benighted: And wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering too &amp; froe, he eſpyed at the laſte a candle ſhyninge from the ſyde of a rock: thither he wente with all haſt, &amp; called of them within. By and by there came forthe a fatherly
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:25031:11"/>oulde man named <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> &amp; aſked who he was that called ſo vntymelye at his Cell? I am a pilgrime for the holy lande ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> &amp; goinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray in this wildernes, I eſpyed by good happ your candle, &amp; am come to craue harbour with you this night. All that come in godds name be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to me ſayd <hi>Alphonſo.</hi> I thanke you good Father ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they were come within the Cell &amp; ſett downe, eche behelde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther verie earneſtly. And <hi>Probus</hi> ſaid, I meruell good Father, how you can endure to liue this auſtere lyfe in your comſe attyre of ſack cloath, with ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fayre in this vneaſie hoale. I haue endured it ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> theſe many yeres I thanke God, and during this mortall lyfe, I deſyre noe change. In what ſorte I pray you ſaide <hi>Probus,</hi> haue you ſpent your lyfe in this ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, &amp; what buſines haue you had to kepe you here thus long? This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lyfe ſeemeth verye horrible to mannes nature. Mannes nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede my ſonne ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> would
<pb facs="tcp:25031:11"/>not endure this, if it were not drawn on &amp; fedd with greater comforthe an other way.</p>
               <p>The onely buſines wherein I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow my ſelf in this place, is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſerue my Lord &amp; God: which trade of lyfe, is to me ſo ſweete, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, &amp; profitable, that it ouercometh all the horrour, payne, &amp; other diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, which the frailtie of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fyndeth. What excedinge ioyes alſo I haue by the hope of myne eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reward with God for ſeruing him as I doe (if by his grace I perſeuer to the ende) my tonge can not expreſſe.</p>
               <p>It ſemeth ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> your ſeruing of God is more then ordinary: For I ſerue him alſo as I thinke, yet haue I not any ſuch ioy therein as you ſpeake of. My dyetr is daintie, myne appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ryche, my howſe ſumptuous, and yet with all theſe, I fynde ſmall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or eaſe in ſeruing God.</p>
               <p>Theſe temporall commodities ſaide <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I want voluntarilye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it beſt pleaſeth my Lorde that I ſo doe, &amp; that I be content with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25031:12"/>without encombring my ſelf with ſuch ſuperfluous thinges as you ſpeake of, which if I had or deſyred, woulde pethapps much hinder me in godds ſeruice, &amp; are aſſuredly nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, to my lyfe, health, or good eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: But the perfect ſeruice of God, which bringeth to man true comforth delight, &amp; beneftte in this lyfe, and a ioyfull hope of ineſtimable rewarde in heauen, conſiſteth not in the wante or hauing of theſe temporall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: For you alſo in your welth and abundance (if you knew the way) mighte perhapps ſerue God with as much pleaſure &amp; benefite, as I doe in this pouertie wherein you ſee me liue. For our Sauiour ſaid: <hi>Bleſſed be the poore in ſpirit, becauſe theirs is the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</hi> Which happy bleſſing &amp; pouertie not onely they may enioy that wante all earthly treaſures &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities: But alſo the greateſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the worlde, in the middeſt of their wealth &amp; abundance.</p>
               <p>If this be ſo ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> I beſeche you teach me the way, for I confeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:25031:12"/>I know it not: &amp; if I can learne this leſſon, I think I haue greate aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of you, that liue thus auſterely in this deſert. Perhapps noe great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> for it is noe leſſe gratefull &amp; acceptable vnto god &amp; noe leſſe meritorious to our ſelues, to forſake all temporall commodities for his ſeruice, then to poſſeſſe &amp; vſe them to the ſame ende: yea the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of man and the corruption of our natures conſidered, it is muche leſſe perill to want them then to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the more we encomber &amp; diſtract our ſmall abilities abowt earthly thigs the leſſe able are we to attende and wholly yelde our ſelues to heauenly.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall willingly teach you the beſt way of ſeruinge God that hitherto I haue knowne. Sett aſyde therefore all other thoughtes; &amp; marke well what I ſhall ſay. When you conceaue me not, aſke bouldly what my meaning is: For it is loſt tyme to vs both, if I proceede, &amp; teach more then you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande. Good Father ſaid <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> ſeing you geue me leaue, I will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25031:13"/>make bould to interrupt you when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I conceaue you not, or doubt in any poynte. So doe in godds name ſaid <hi>Alphonſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then I muſt lay you downe a few conſiderations &amp; inſtructions, of great importance, and which are the foundations &amp; groundwork whereon we muſt ſtay &amp; raiſe vpp all the frame we are to buylde. And you muſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and verey carefullye call them to mynde, if you think to profitt in this way of ſeruing God I ſhall doe my beſt endeuour therein ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2 (instruction 1)" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FIRST INSTRVCTI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, ſhewing to what ende God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Man, &amp; placed him vpon earth. CAP. 2</head>
               <p>THe firſt inſtruction ſaid <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> &amp; the foundation of all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten &amp; ſeriouſly to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is, that God (as the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures and Fathers teach) created and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25031:13"/>ſent vs into this world, not to enioy &amp; reſt in the tranſitory commodities &amp; pleaſures thereof: but that (taking of godds creatures ſo muche as may ſuffyce our neceſſities) we occupy &amp; beſtow our ſelues and all the reſte we haue, in ſeruing &amp; honoring our lord, who haith prepared for our rewarde, the bliſſe of heauen, wherein we ſhall poſſeſſe for euer, God him ſelf, that is, an infinite good, and in him, all good thinges more aboundantly then we can imagin. To honour &amp; ſerue God therfore (my ſonn) are we come into this world. All we doo beſydes this is nothing els but loſte laboure, vaine &amp; hurtfull tryfling, diſhonora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the noble children of ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as God is. No doubt father ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> but we were created to ſerue God as you ſay: But what kynde of ſeruice dothe God requyre of man, &amp; is by man of bounde &amp; dutie to be performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3 (instruction 2)" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25031:14"/>
               <head>THE SECOND INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of two manners how to ſerue god, &amp; how Man is bounde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. CAP. 3.</head>
               <p>THere be two ſortes of ſeruinge god ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> &amp; two waies in lyke manner are we bounde to ſerue him. The ſirſte is in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of godds commaundementes, which we are all bounde to kepe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of eternall damnation to hell fyre. The ſecond is more perfect, &amp; is this, that (forſakinge all earthlye thinges, and withdrawinge our hartes from the loue thereof) we caſte oure affection wholly vpon our heauenlye Father which is an infinite goodnes, &amp; in all thinges laboure to be of the ſame ſpirit &amp; will with him, accordinge to the example which our Sauioure the naturall Sonn of God left vs whiles he ſerued here on earth, not for any nede of his owne, but to inſtruct vs how we
<pb facs="tcp:25031:14"/>ought to ſerue our Lorde. This way Chriſt taught the yong man which had kept the commaundementes when he ſaid, <hi>If thou wilt be perfect, geue all thou haſt to the poore, &amp; com &amp; folow me.</hi> How are Chriſtians bounde to this manner of ſeruice ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not vnder payne of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> as in the firſt way, but by a Law of frendſhipp with god of equity &amp; gratitude, wherein all the children of God that woulde not be reckned baſe-minded, vngratefull, &amp; fooliſh, ſhould moſte carefully keepe them ſelues, that they may appere the worthy children of ſo graceous a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For to all it is geuen in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, that we loue our Lord with all our ſoule, with all our hart, with all our minde, and with all our ſtrength. And to all he ſaid: <hi>Be you perfect as your heauenly Father is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As he deſerueth much blame that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſom place for diſpatch of ſom weightie &amp; neceſſary affaires, &amp; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting &amp; leauing the thing he wente to doe, trifleth away his tyme in vyle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25031:15"/>ſportes &amp; abiect thinges: ſo likewiſe is he much blame worthy, that being borne into this world to ſerue the high maieſtie of God with all his powers &amp; abilities, (which ſeruice is moſt due vnto God, &amp; moſt profitable to the ſeruant) yet omittethe it becauſe it is not commaunded him vnder paine of death, beſtowing him ſelf in the mean ſeaſon, in a meaner and more abiecte kynde of ſeruice, mixed with muche worldly vanitie, that moſt ſwiftly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, &amp; bringethe with it much euill. And albeit God haith left it in our free choice and curtefye, yet the bound of frendſhipp, equitie &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, requireth that we endeuoure to ſerue him (to whom all honour and ſeruice is moſt due) in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we are able. The firſt way to ſerue God ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> is plame &amp; manifeſt to all Chriſtians, but the other apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth onely to you Eremites, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons, and Clargie men.</p>
               <p>As the firſt ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Chriſtians, &amp; taught eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where: ſo there is no Chriſtian but
<pb facs="tcp:25031:15"/>he may be taught, learn, &amp; performe the ſeconde. I can hardly think ſo ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for we may not all forſake the world &amp; caſt all our hartes vpon this perfect ſeruinge of God you ſpeake of. No perſon ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is made a Chriſtian, before he firſt ſolemnly renownce the worlde, with all the pompes &amp; vanities thereof, &amp; yelde him ſelf to the obedience &amp; ſeruice of God. And therefore the profeſſion, not onely of Ermits, religious perſons &amp; Prieſtes: but of all true Chriſtians alſo, is to forſake the world, &amp; ſerue their Lord with all they are &amp; haue. For as I ſaid God created man for this ende, &amp; for all temporall &amp; earthly things, no man doth rightly vſe them or can haue them, but to his excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge harme, vnleſſe he turne them wholly to the ſeruice, &amp; honoure of his Lorde, whoſe in truth they be &amp; not mannes but for a litle tyme to vſe as god haith ordeyned &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which ſeruice we ought to yeld to God, not onely in keping his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall commaundements, but in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25031:16"/>perfecteſt manner, as Chriſt our Lord by his owne exawple haith taught vs all. And this ſeconde is that, which now I purpoſe to teach you, that is, how ryche men, artificers, &amp; all ſorts of people, may ſerue their Lord and God moſt perfectlye. This will be moſt comfortable to vs of the world ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> but it ſemeth a moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult thing to be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4 (instruction 3)" type="chapter">
               <head>THE THIRD INSTRVCTION Of the wofull ruine &amp; deſtruction made in mannes ſoule &amp; body by ſinne, by reaſon whereof, he fyndeth greate difficultye in ſeruinge God. CAP. 4</head>
               <p>YOu muſt know moreouer ſaide <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that if man had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the happy ſtate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God created him at the firſt when he placed him in paradiſe, it had bene noe difficultie for him, to haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God in moſt perfect manner, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25031:16"/>to haue wrought any good. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by originall iuſtice, his ſeſuality &amp; inferior powers were kept in moſt ſemely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; perfect obedience to his reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; will. And theſe againe were guyded &amp; aſſiſted, by ſingular &amp; abundante graces, eaſily to obey &amp; ſerue God &amp; woorke any good. But after once by the euill vſe of his free will, he ſinned &amp; tranſgreſſed the commaundement of his Lord: he with all his progeny were ſpoyled of thoſe graceous giftes &amp; caſt owt of that happy ſtate &amp; place into the baniſhment of this miſerable worlde. His appetites, his will, and whole ſoule, became ſo infirme &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, that (loathing the infinite good for which he was created, as a thinge wherein now he tooke noe delight or pleaſant taſte, &amp; auerſt from all good) he is euer ſince inclyned to euill, and can deſyre or loue ſcarſly any other thinges, but abiect, viceous, &amp; hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. By reaſon of that greauous loſſe &amp; wofull chaunge, mankynde euer ſince haith founde much difficultie in the ſeruice of god, or doinge well.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25031:17"/>
               <p>Our concupiſcence and inferioure powers, being now for want of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall iuſtice, lett looſe and ſett at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: neuer ceaſe mightily to repugne and diſobey, the reaſonable partes of our ſoule: yea &amp; to draw them to any thinge they lyke, withowt regard what either reaſon or God commaundeth.</p>
               <p>We haue ſtill left vs ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> the powers of our reaſon and free will, and God geuethe the aſſiſtance of his grace to all that call for it: by theſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may ſerue God in the beſt manner he requyrethe, notwithſtandinge the corruption &amp; repugnance of our infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour powers. We may ſerue him ſo indeede ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but not with ſuch facilitie, promptnes, &amp; alacritie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as we might haue done in the ſtate of our innocency. For not onely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations &amp; motions of our ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be verie diſordered &amp; contrary to oure reaſon, yea excedinglye impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune &amp; vehemente to drawe vs from good to euill: but our reaſon alſo is much darkned, by that fall from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall iuſtice, &amp; our will ſore weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:25031:17"/>and wounded, yea and of them ſelues quyte diſabled either to reſiſte the continuall aſſaultes of oure ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie &amp; inferiour partes, or effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to woorke any good. The grace of god indeede enableth vs to doe well, but yet (as it is ordinarilye beſtowed on men) it takethe not from them, nor quite ouercometh, the repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; difficulties, which our corrupte natures haue in doing well. Can we not ſaid <hi>Probus</hi> ouercom this difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by any meanes? Yea in great part ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> by ſinguler &amp; extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary graces geuen by God, &amp; by the good habits of vertues which we may plant in our ſoules, by diligent exerciſe of our ſuperiour powers as I ſhall tell you hereafter. But now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that this great confuſion and perturbation in our ſoules, our auerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from good, our inclination to euill, with difficulty of woorking well, came all from ſinn: &amp; yet the ſame bounde of doing well &amp; ſeruing God which we had before this deſtruction, is not taken away from vs. For though we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25031:18"/>not doe our duties but with much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie, yet doe them we may by the aſſiſtance of godds grace, &amp; by litle and litle, repayre againe the loſſe and wrack we haue gotten by ſinn, in oure ſoule &amp; appetites. How may this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration be made ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for I think the nearer we bring our ſoules &amp; powers to their former ſtate, the better ſhall we be diſpoſed, and with more facilitie ſhall we be able to doe our duties in ſeruing God. Yea more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer ſaid <hi>Allphonſo,</hi> we may profitt ſo muche herein, that we may obteyne wel-neare the ſame facilitie to worke with great delight in this corruptible lyfe, which we ſhould haue had in the ſtate of innocency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5 (instruction 4)" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FOVRTH INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, by what powers of our ſoule, we may repayre our ruyne, &amp; of the way howe to vſe oure vnderſtanding and will.
<pb facs="tcp:25031:18"/> CAP. <hi>5</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN what manner ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> is this Reparation to be made? It can not be made otherwyſe ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but by the powers and abilities of our ſoule helped &amp; aſſiſted with the grace of God. Wherefore you muſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that as man is made, and conſiſteth of a body &amp; ſoule: ſo haith he infirmities in them both to woorke with, as the body haith feete to goe, handes to labour, tonge to ſpeake, &amp; the lyke. In the ſoule, there is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; will, with diuers other ſenſuall powers. The corporall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and their actions of them ſelues, are of ſmall wotth &amp; litle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid to <hi>Timothy.</hi> But the vnderſtandinge and the will, may of their owne natures, be of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent dignitie &amp; profitt, as if we oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy them to know God &amp; loue him, or to conſider any good thing, and to deſyre it, or to know what is euill, &amp; to hate &amp; ſhunne it: which operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25031:19"/>of theſe two powers, are greatly commodious, though the body reſte all the while &amp; do nothing. For by the Exerciſe of ſuche actions abowte any particuler vertue, we ſhould produce &amp; bring forth good habits in our ſoule &amp; deſtroy the euill, which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thinge, though it be done but onely for the loue of vertue, as the heathen Philoſophers did: much more when a Chriſtian doth it hauing faith: but moſte of all if ſuch a man doe it with actuall intention, for the loue, honour, &amp; ſeruice of God, as I ſhall declare anone.</p>
               <p>Theſe two inſtruments therefore, the vnderſtanding &amp; the will, &amp; their operations, are the meanes (goddes grace euer concurring with vs) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we may perfectly ſerue God and woorke the reparation of our ſoule.</p>
               <p>They be indeede ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> the cheifeſt and moſte noble powers that man haith, and therefore fitteſte for ſuch an ende: but in what ſort ſhould we vſe them rightly? Our ſenſuall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> naturally deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:25031:19"/>the thinge which it is inclined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that is, what ſoeuer ſemeth vnto it pleaſant, delectable, and ſweete for the preſent, to theſe naturally it is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried without further reſpecte: And in like ſort it fleeth whatſoeuer ſeemethe harde, ſharpe, and vnpleaſante.</p>
               <p>But our will is not moued in this ſort, for before it deſyre or ſhunn any thing, it conſulteth with the vnderſtanding, whether the thinge be conueniente or not, and according as the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, iudgeth, ſo the will freely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth or refuſethe it: So that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge, is as it were, a lighte and guyde to the will, ſhewinge the truth of euery thing as it conceiue the it, &amp; directinge the will how to work.</p>
               <p>Wherefore aboue all other things we muſt be carefull, that our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doe not erre or be deceiued in any thinge we goe abowt to deſyre or ſhunne. For if it be blinded by ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, paſſion, or malice: it can neuer iudge rightly, nor conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the action of the will euer be good.</p>
               <p>But againe, though the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25031:20"/>be without errour &amp; iudge tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what the thing is, or ſhew rightly what is to be done in any occaſion: yet ſo meruelous is the power of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s will, that it ſtandeth in free libertie, to folow, &amp; woork as the reaſon iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or to refuſe. Onely it of all other powers and abilityes in man, haithe fredom &amp; perfect libertie. It is ſubiect to none, &amp; commaundeth all the reſt: yea and in a meruelous ſort the ſame power can predominate ouer it ſelfe, both freely commaund and enforce it ſelfe to obey: ſo that hereupon cometh all our euill, if either the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge erre, or (it iudging rightlye) the will by reaſon of her lidertie, will not woorke accordingly. In this ſort therefore we muſt proceede with theſe two powers for the reparation of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>And firſt for the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing which either by our naturall teaſon, or by the light of our faith, we know to be good, or diſpoſing or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering vs to vertue, &amp; neuertheleſſe we fynde great difficultie, horrour, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25031:20"/>auerſion in our ſelues to doe or deſire it as were for our good: we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vſe the power of our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; with it, conſider and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende, thoſe ſame thinges (which ſeeme ſo ſharpe &amp; greuous to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) as thinges moſt preceous, and to God alſo moſt acceptable, &amp; which may further vs alſo, to eternall life &amp; ioyes: And after once we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered &amp; knowne them to be ſuche, the will which had auerſion and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of them before, may now be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to loue, deſyre, &amp; embrace them, &amp; to worke them in effect.</p>
               <p>When they are thus conſidered &amp; knowne to be ſuch ſaid <hi>Probus:</hi> yet is the will free to chooſe, to doe them or not. You ſay truly ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> the will euer remaineth free, &amp; haith perfect dominion &amp; libertie to doe, or not to doe: but yet often it is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed with the difficultie &amp; ſharpnes of the thinge which is offered to it, &amp; therupon ceaſeth to woorke, and ſo ſinneth or omitteth the good that it might haue done. But if we endeour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25031:21"/>by our vnderſtanding, to prepare the way in manner aboueſaid, it will take ſuch courage vpon the knowledge of the excellencye of that woorke, that (be it neuer ſo painefull) it will loue and deſyre it, and doe it alſo with as much facilitie and delighte welnere, as any other thinge which it coueteth naturally. Mark this pointe well my ſonne, for I aſſure you that he which would worke &amp; vſe his vnderſtanding in this manner, ſhoulde eaſely and in ſhorte tyme, come to great perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vertue, &amp; woork with much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light &amp; comforth. I think it well ſaid <hi>Probus:</hi> But may I intreate you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me this by ſome example?</p>
               <p>With good will ſaid <hi>Alphonſo:</hi> but it will fall more conuenientlye after I haue ſhewed you how alſo you muſte vſe your will, for this is the cheifeſt poynt of all. Then proceede I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25031:21"/>
                  <head>THE Vſe of the will.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſing ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> goddes holy grace euer to aſſiſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr with ourfree will (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe we were not able to thinke any good expediente for our ſaluation, muche leſſe to deſyre &amp; woorke the ſame) you muſt know that it is in our owne power to deſyre or leaue to de deſyre, any thing iudged good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by our vnderſtanding, &amp; the ſame we may doe for this or that ende, and as often euery day as we will.</p>
                  <p>Nowe to wake the will deſyre to doe a good thinge which naturally it doth abhorr, by reaſon perhapps it is painefull, harde, or vnpleaſante: we muſt (as I ſaid before) conſider &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende the ſame thinge, as moſte preceous &amp; gratefull to God, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to our ſelues: &amp; then incline our will (enforcing it after a ſorte) to deſyre &amp; couet that thinge, as a ſick man deſyreth a bitter potion, becauſe he apprehendeth it as holeſome, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25031:22"/>which narurally he doth loth and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr. In like manner alſo is produced the acte of refuſing or not deſiring the euill, which we naturally couet or are inclined vnto; that conſideringe it to be vngratefull to God, euill &amp; hurtfull to our ſelues, we incline our will, &amp; as it were violently enforce it, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that thing. For example, to couet to be deſpyſed, contemned, or litle eſtemed among men, is a thinge hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, vnpleaſant, &amp; difficulte to our nature: And in like manner to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all ſenſuall delights &amp; pleaſures.</p>
                  <p>Now he that woulde haue an acte of deſiring ſuch contempts &amp; wantes of pleaſures; muſt firſt conſider and apprehend them, as moſt excellente &amp; worthy thinges, moſt gratefull to God, &amp; greatly meritorious to him ſelfe, &amp; then compell as it were and enforce his will, to accept and deſire them. In lyke ſorte alſo to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, highly eſtemed, &amp; be loued of all men, to haue ſenſuall pleaſures &amp; other thinges delightfull, ſweete, &amp; pleaſant to our nature: He that would
<pb facs="tcp:25031:22"/>make an acte of refuſinge and hatinge them, muſt conſider and iudge them with his vnderſtanding, as thinges of baſe valew, diſpleaſant &amp; vngratefull to God, &amp; hurtfull to him ſelf. And then vpon this true conceipt of theſe harmes in them, ceaſe to deſire them &amp; make an act of hatred or contempt of them, as the ſick perſon doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr &amp; refuſe a moſt ſweete potion or other meate pleaſing his appetite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knoweth it to be hurtfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, though otherwyſe he had a vehement naturall deſire &amp; inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſame.</p>
                  <p>In vſing our vnderſtanding &amp; will in this manner ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſhall we feele noe repugnance in our ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Yes ſaid <hi>Alphonſo</hi> &amp; that often verie greate, but this not-withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, our acte is a true deſire or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall of our will: As we behoulde in the ſicke man, that will not eate the meate to which he haith a greate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection &amp; appetite, becauſe it is vnhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for him, and that ſame will of his not to eate it, is profitable vnto him,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25031:23"/>though his inordinate appetite be not taken away. But by often woorking with the will in that ſorte, the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance &amp; all difficulties, will be leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned daily by the good habitts we get by our particuler actions. And albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it we ſeme litle to profitt or goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, &amp; to fynde ſmall pleaſure in woorking thus, by reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vitious habitts, inclinations, &amp; cuſtoms in our ſoule, which make our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions ſeme weake &amp; could: yet muſt we not ceaſe to doe them, for by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe &amp; exerciſe, we gett dailye more ſtrength &amp; readines, and we goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with great meritt.</p>
                  <p>Is this all ſaid <hi>Probus</hi> I am to learn abowt the vſe of theſe two powers?</p>
                  <p>This which I haue toulde you ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is the way to vſe them: but one thinge more I muſte tell you, which all that woulde perfectly &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly repayre their ſoules, muſt with greate diligence, carrie in minde and practiſe: for it is as it were the key of all our reparation. What is this I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi> My ſonne ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:25031:23"/>it is that beſides the continuall ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; care we ought to haue of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſinge the will, in deſyring the good thinges we ſhould deſire, &amp; omitting the deſire of euill thinges, thereby to deſtroy euill habitts in our ſoule, and plante good, that beſides this I ſay, we be diligent by the vſe of our will, to repreſſe &amp; reſiſt the firſt thoughtes, motions, &amp; appetites, which often aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile euen vertuous perſons, and which may be conſented vnto withowt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne. As for example, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted that our deedes or woordes, be well eſtemed, or to be ſorowfull &amp; diſpleaſed for iniuries, &amp; auerſion of other perſons from vs, &amp; ſuch lyke: In all which, though it be not a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinne, that we be occupyed or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente to them, yet fewe knowe what great loſſe &amp; harme they bringe to vs, for by them our ſoule is made dull &amp; heauy towardes good thinges it ſhould doe. He therefore that deſyre the to be lorde ouer his owne actions, &amp; be able with facility to worke well: ought preſently with his will, to reſiſt theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25031:24"/>firſt motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: That where he was aſſayled with a motion of greif for ſuch iniuries &amp; auerſion, or ſuche lyke: he preſently oppoſe him ſelf &amp; reſiſt ſuch ſorow &amp; greif, with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall deſyre of iniuries, vexations, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt, &amp; contradiction. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trari-wyſe in the motions of honour, creditt, fauour, &amp; all other ſweete, &amp; delectable thinges, wherupon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently arryſeth in vs a complacency &amp; delight: We muſt be ready by &amp; by to woorke with our will an acte of not deſyring or delighting in ſuch thinges as naturally we are inclyned vnto and couett. For by ſo doinge, we ſhall not onely eſcape vanitie &amp; ſinn but by often practiſe, &amp; vſe, obteyne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent habitts, &amp; expell the euill. Marke this well, &amp; it may ſuffiſe for this poynt &amp; inſtruction.</p>
                  <p>I perceiue ſaid Probus, thoſe good habitts woulde take away all or moſte of our difficultie in woorkinge well: What way then may we gett them?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall teach you this alſo by &amp; by ſaide <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but firſte I muſte tell
<pb facs="tcp:25031:24"/>you what intention &amp; ende you muſt haue in the vſe of your powers, &amp; in all your actions; for without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of this, all you can doe, will be to ſmall purpoſe or commoditie.</p>
                  <p>I pray you lett me here it then ſaid <hi>Probus</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6 (instruction 5)" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FIFTH INSTRVCTION, What ende, ſcope, &amp; intention, the ſeruante of God ſhoulde haue in all his actions. CAP. 6.</head>
               <p>YOu muſte know therefore ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> That in all thinges which we deſyre or doe, the ende, intention, and motiue, why we doe it, maketh the acte good or euill preceous in goddes ſight &amp; meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or vyle &amp; ſinfull: In ſo much as a good woork done for an euill ende, is euill, though otherwiſe of it owne nature it were good.</p>
               <p>Doth a good ende in like manner ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> make an euill woorke good?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:25031:25"/>
               <p>Not ſo ſaide <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> For as a good woorke muſt be euery way void of euill, as wel, in it owne nature, as in the ende for which it is done: So an euill woorke is made euill, either for that it is euill of it own nature, or done for ſome euill ende. For which cauſe the Apoſtle ſaid, that it was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to doe euill, for a good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Goe forwarde ſaid <hi>Probus</hi> for I vnderſtande this.</p>
               <p>Euery woork ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that is good of it owne nature, or that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, that is, which being neither good nor euill of it ſelfe: may yet be made good by a good ende or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or euill by an euill ende. Euery ſuch woorke I ſay, may be done or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred for diuers good endes, as for the loue of vertue, or for the benefite of our ſelues or our neighboures, or for the imitation of our Sauiour and his Sainctes, or finallye for the loue of God, &amp; thereby to ſerue, pleaſe, &amp; honour him.</p>
               <p>Now as one ende is better then an other: So conſequently, that woorke
<pb facs="tcp:25031:25"/>is better, which is done for a better ende, &amp; that the beſt, which is done for the beſt ende. Wherfore becauſe god is an infinite goodnes, that work is the beſt which is wrought purely &amp; whollye for his ſake, or to yelde him honour or ſeruice, without reſpect of any other ende. The ſeruant of god then that deſyreth in the beſt manner to pleaſe &amp; ſerue his Lord, muſt doe all thinges both in body &amp; ſoule, for God, to pleaſe, ſerue, obey, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him thereby: That (forgeating as it were the good &amp; glory that may come to our ſelues by doing any acte of vertue, &amp; mindfull onely of God which deſyreth our well doinge, and delighteth in it, &amp; is moſt worthy to be ſerued &amp; honored by vs in euery thing) we be moued to woork one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for pleaſing &amp; honoringe him, and for fulfilling his will: Like to a man, that for recouering his owne healthe, haith prepared a medicine, &amp; before he take it, perceauing his deare frend to be fallen ſick, and to haue greater neede of the ſame: In this caſe (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geating
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25031:26"/>as it were his owne infirmity, &amp; the deſire he had to that medicine, &amp; mindefull onely of his frende) he reioyceth to forgoe it himſelfe, &amp; to beſtow it for releeuinge of his frendes neceſſitye: So ſhould we I ſay againe, ſerue God, &amp; euer (forgeating our ſelues &amp; all other things) deſyre and woorke onely, becauſe it is godds will we doe it, &amp; becauſe his maieſty requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it at our handes. For this ende &amp; motiue we ſhoulde couet to loue god, deſyre vertues, deſyre &amp; pray for pardon of our ſinnes, for graces, for glory: For this ende we ſhoulde flee ſinne, feare hell, abhorr damnation, &amp; deſyre or refuſe whatſoeuer. It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth harde &amp; vnpleaſant at the firſt, but after a whyle, it will be eaſie and delightfull. And ſuch as haue their wills enflammed with deuotion &amp; the loue of god, at the firſte hearinge of this way, can woork thus without difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and in ſhort time come to exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great perfection.</p>
               <p>But how ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſhall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which haue but coulde deuotion,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:26"/>and weake loue of God, com to get this motiue actually in all they doe?</p>
               <p>They may gett it ſaid <hi>Alphouſo</hi> by the vſe of their vnderſtandinge &amp; will in this ſort. Lett them conſider, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, &amp; ſett God as their cheifeſt frende &amp; moſt worthy Lorde on the one ſyde, and them ſelues on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This done, when theire will is moued to couet any vertue, or doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good woorke: Let them conſider for what ende they are moued, and they ſhall finde it vſually, either for feare of puniſhment, or for their own benefite, or for the loue of vertue, or deſyre of heauenly bliſſe. None of theſe motiues ſhoulde ſuffice or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the ſeruant of God, though they be not euill: But ſeinge his will is ſo free (goddes help euer preſuppoſed) that it may refuſe any one ende, and chooſe an other, as I tould you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And ſeinge alſo he beleeuethe godds will to be more excellent and worthy, &amp; that it ſhould moue him rather then his owne: He muſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently enforce him ſelf to omitt &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25031:27"/>to deſyre or will any thinge after his wonted ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner &amp;, bring his will to deſyre the ſame thing for a better end &amp; motyue, that is, to deſyre to doe it, for fulfillinge the bleſſed will of God &amp; pleaſing him, and for that he (worthy of all ſeruice, obeyſance, &amp; honour) would haue him to doe it.</p>
               <p>This loe is the way to gett this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine motiue in all our actions, which ſo incomparably excellethe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of our owne naturall deſyres, &amp; all other motiues (how good &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſoeuer they be) as noe tong ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſe. For the perfection of all our holines &amp; charitie, conſiſteth in this poynte, that we conforme our ſelues in all thinges to godds will, &amp; be of the ſame mynde with him. For which cauſe, and for that it is Goddes high pleaſure &amp; deſyre, that vpon this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true we ferue him: we ſhoulde ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to haue it in all our workes both corporall &amp; ſpirituall both greate and ſmall: yea in thoſe alſo which we are naturally to woork according to gods ordinance, as to eate, ſleepe, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:27"/>
               <p>For as we can not leaue theſe vndone: ſo doing them for the loue of God, they helpe vs much to the encreaſe of our ſpirituall lyfe: And ſo the leaſte woorke that we doe in Godds ſight, as to eate, ſlepe, recreate, &amp; the like: ſhall be of more dignitye, then the greateſte woorke which he doth that haith not the ſame ende: as to faſte, to watch, to geue almes, to afflict the bodie, &amp; ſuch like, for the kingdom &amp; ioyes of heauen, or any other end be it neuerſo good.</p>
               <p>Thus may we excedingly enriche ourſelues euery day: thus may we be made as it were diuine, when we are moued in all our actions, onely by the ſpiritt &amp; will of God. And therefore when we are abowt to doe any thing we ſhould not paſſe vnaduiſedly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on thinge to an other, nor euer begin any thing, without caſting of our eies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon God: nor be contente and ſatiſfyed with this neither, till we feele our ſelues to will &amp; deſyre the worke for pleaſinge God, who excedinglye ioyeth &amp; delighteth in our well doing,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25031:28"/>which once perceiued and ſenſiblye knowne, lett vs ſett vpon the woork we are to doe, without thinkinge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any good of our owne. For it is fitt &amp; due, that his omnipotente and bleſſed will that created all wills, haue ſuch precminence &amp; dominion ouer all wills, that not onely they obey him in all he haithe commaunded them: but moreouer, that they doe euery thinge they are to woork, for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his holy will, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect. At the beginning it will ſeme verye difficult &amp; harde to worke vpon this motiue, &amp; ſmall deuotion or ioy will appeare in this Exercyſe: &amp; the reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, for that we woorke not now, nor loue not, for any good of our owne, as we were accuſtomed to doe, &amp; as it is naturall to vs: But woorking onely for the loue of God, we as it were remoue away from vs, the roote from which all ioye and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, was vſually &amp; naturally wont to ſpring, that is, we leaue all reſpect of our owne proper good &amp; reſt, &amp; take for the reſt &amp; ende of all our labours,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:28"/>an vnuſuall or ſtraunge good, that is, the ſeruice, pleaſure, glory, or loue of God: which being a ſupernaturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue &amp; ende, and ſtraunge to vs at the firſte, noe meruell if this chaunge, bringe vnto vs great paine &amp; trouble at the beginning: But by daily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, &amp; frequent actions, we ſhall gett an habitt thereof &amp; woorke readilye, with much delighte &amp; comforth.</p>
               <p>I beleue it well ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for all beginnings of good things, are euer difficult &amp; vnpleaſant: and diligent vſe &amp; practiſe, make promptnes.</p>
               <p>But I pray you Father, lett me aſk you two queſtions, firſte how ſhall I know and be aſſured, that it is godds holy will &amp; deſyre, that I woorke in this manner, and ſerue him vpon this motiue, and for this ende in all things?</p>
               <p>This may you know ſaid <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> both by your naturall reaſon, and the light of our Catholick Faith. For God created vs all to ſerue him, and greatly deſyreth, yea moſte ſtrictlye chargeth vs to loue him, with all our hartes and abilities. And becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25031:29"/>his dreadfull Maieſty, is worthy of the cheifeſt and beſt ſeruice &amp; in the beſt manner alſo that his creatures can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe, to yelde him, which is, to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in our actions, and to doe all we doe, for his loue, will, and honoure, as him ſelf doth in all his woorkes: It is manifeſt that his will &amp; deſyre is, that we imitate him, working and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him in all thinges, for the ſame motiue and ende. For nothing can be more acceptable to his maieſtie, then that we conforme our ſelues to him, and doe all for his ſake. What is your other queſtion now ſaid <hi>Alphonſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why then ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> is not this ende and motiue (being the moſt perfect of all other) commaunded or taught vs in the holie Scriptures, but for the moſte parte, they threaten vs with puniſhment, or muite vs with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? &amp;c. The Sonn of god our Sauiour Ieſus ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> as he condeſcended for our good, to take vpon him our infirmities, as to be hungry, weary, to feare, to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, and the lyke: So woulde he
<pb facs="tcp:25031:29"/>alſo haue his eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelicall doctrine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in ſuch woords, as our baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and frailtie requyred: which for the moſt part is moued (now after the corruption of our natures by originall ſinne) either by hope of good rewards or for feare of puniſhment. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we muſt conſider, that as our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer tooke vpon him thoſe infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of oure nature, with the cheefeſte perfection and charitie that might be, in fulfilling the will of his Father by doinge and ſufferinge all for his loue and glory: ſo he would haue his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to folow his example: And (that hearing godds threates or promiſes) they be indeede woued with them, &amp; doe their beſt to eſcape the one, and gett the other: but all this, not for the paines and puniſhmente threatned, or the rewardes promiſed: but becauſe they procede by them, that it is godds will &amp; deſyre, they laboure to eſcape paynes and damnation, in which ſtate they can neuer ſerue God more, nor doe his will: and to obteine the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of heauen, where they ſhall be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25031:30"/>with God for euer, and haue noe will, but to honour and praiſe him. So the ſinner once brought to grace, feareth godds threates, becauſe his will is, that he feare them: He doth pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe it is godds will he doe it: He doth good woorkes for heauen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is godds will he ſo doe: By reaſon of which ende &amp; motiue, in his actions, they are of moſt high perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and meritt. And ſo the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures though they ſhew that owtward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is agreable to our infirmitie: yet with-all they conteyne inwardlye, their higheſt perfection in this poynte, as is manifeſt in the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t geuen, that we loue our Lorde with all our hartes and ſtrength in all things, <note place="margin">Mat. 12</note> which is perfectly kept, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre godds will to be fulfilled. But becauſe out natures are much incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to euill, and by reaſon of our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious habitts and euill cuſtomes, we waxe ſoone weary of well doinge: I muſt teach you how to extirpate ſuch euill habitts owt of your ſoule, and to engraft good: For vnleſſe you learne
<pb facs="tcp:25031:30"/>this, all we haue ſaid hitherto is to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe, and you ſhall neuer worke with alacritie of mynde, nor procede with profitt. Doe ſo I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for in all your ſpeach hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I haue perceiued that good habits woulde take away either all, or the moſt part of difficulties, which are to be founde in ſeruing God this perfect way you haue taught me. They do ſo ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> and more-ouer, the whole reparation of our ſoule, conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in them, as the wrack &amp; deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all oure good, is by the euill habitts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7 (instruction 6)" type="chapter">
               <head>THE SIXTE INSTRVCTION. How to plante good habitts in our ſoule, &amp; extirpate the euill. CAP. 7</head>
               <p>YOu muſt know therfore ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> that as theſe habitts be in our ſoules: ſo the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; made, are wrought principally, by the powers or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25031:31"/>of the ſoule. And vnleſſe we diligently vſe &amp; exerciſe theſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, eſpecially our vnderſtanding &amp; will, we ſhall neuer gett the habitts of any vertues. As for example, if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be impatient or teſtye, &amp; would haue this vice amended in him ſelf, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the habitt of patience, this man how much ſoeuer he be wronged with iniurious woordes or deedes: howe much ſoeuer he deſire the habitt of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, yea how much ſoeuer he refrain from woordes or deedes of reuenge: yet ſhall he neuer produce or bringe forth in his ſoule, the habitt of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, except he help him ſelf by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mouinge his vnderſtanding, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the great good of patience, and by ſtirring his will as the neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to bring forth this habitt by inclyning it (as I ſaid before) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to ſuffer iniuries and perſecutions for the loue, pleaſure, and glorie of his Lord, that exhorteth vs all to it, and haith ſuffered the lyke for vs.</p>
               <p>Liuing among good and ciuill peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> and Chriſtians eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:25031:31"/>that haue the feare of God: we ſhall verye ſeldome, haue any ſuche occaſions of impatience offered vs by iniurious woords or deedes, &amp; ſo ſhall we haue ſmall exerciſe, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be long in getting the habitt of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, or neuer gett it at all. In like ſort alſo may we ſay, of the habitts of other vertues.</p>
               <p>Not ſo ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> for where or with whom ſoeuer we liue, we may woork, and exerciſe our ſelues at all tymes, to gett any vertuous habitt, &amp; gett it in deede. How may this be ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At all tymes ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> you may produce it thus. For example, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitt of patience. Caſte at any tyme, your cogitation vpon ſom iniury that you much abhorr, and think what you would doe if it were offered or done to you: Preſently you ſhall perceiue, a greate repugnancy and horroure of that iniury aryſe in your minde, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the euill habitt of impatience in you. Forthwith therfore call to minde the great good that foloweth, &amp; how
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25031:32"/>is pleaſed in the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuffering of ſuch iniuries: and then enforce your will to deſyre them. And ceaſe not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force your ſelf to this though it ſeme but a conſtraint and compulſion, for there is euer ſome part voluntary ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And if you practiſe often theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that which ſemed to be but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle voluntary, will increaſe, and you ſhall come to ſuffer iniuries and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation moſt willingly: &amp; withall the habitt of patience will be planted in your ſoule. In lyke manner may you at any tyme plante and enriche your ſelf with habitts of humilitie, of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, Temperance, Chaſtitie, and other vertues, euer conſideringe the greate good that is in the exercyſe of them, and compelling your will to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre them vpon this motiue, becauſe it is the deſyre, will, and glorie of god that you haue them.</p>
               <p>But yet you muſt vnderſtand againe ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that by this forethought and acceptance or deſyre of iniuries, which indeede are not done vs; this habitt of patience is not ſo quickly nor
<pb facs="tcp:25031:32"/>ſo well gotten, as it is when ſom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie or diſgrace is actually done, and this before others, if then you compell your will to accepte it: Becauſe the actions of our will accepting ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent iniuries, are more vehement, &amp; more ſubdue the ſoule, then thoſe which are of accepting an iniurie offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red onely by our thought, &amp; may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, but doth not. And a few vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment actions, woorke more ſtrongly and effectually to the producing of an habitt, then many which are remiſſe and weake.</p>
               <p>This is the way, to roote owt euill habitts, and to plant good. For wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of which effect, it is moreouer greatly profitable, to keepe alwaies a verie firme will and purpoſe, in the deſyre and loue of good, and in the hatred of euill, to which ende ſerue greatly the high conſiderations, and weightie reaſons which many bookes yelde, why good thinges and vertues are to be loued, and vice to be hated.</p>
               <p>Now hereby you may perceiue how the mightieſte Princes of the worlde,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25031:33"/>may enriche them ſelues with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitts of Patience, of Pouertie, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, Temperance, &amp; of all other vertues: and bewtify their Soules in godds ſight, noe leſſe then a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon, if they be willing and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to doe as I haue tould you.</p>
               <p>I perceiue it well ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> but after we perceiue our ſelues to haue gotten theſe good habitts, may we not aſſure our ſelues to be in good ſtate and holy? Albeit ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> a man haue gotten excellente habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of vertues, yet can he not be ſure that he haith gotten the grace of god, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, a man can be in noe good ſtate with him, or in truth holye.</p>
               <p>Godds grace is geuen infalliblye vnto them that haue all which I haue tould you already, and which foloweth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but naturally we can not know in this lyfe, whether we haue theſe things as godds will is we ſhould, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently we can not be certaine, that we haue his fauour and grace. But a cheife ſigne that we haue it is, when in the ſame manner we behaue oure
<pb facs="tcp:25031:33"/>ſelues towardes thoſe vertues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue gotten habitts, as we doe towards the vertues of other men, that is, if our harts be not extolled or any whitt prowde for them, but praiſe &amp; thanke God, whoſe is euery thinge that good is: And ioy as much in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther menns vertues as in oure owne, becauſe godds honour and glory, are equally manifeſted in them both.</p>
               <p>But my ſonn ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geat my ſelf, it is good tyme nowe, you reſt a litle, and make collation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> By this which I haue hitherto ſaid, you may knowe in ſome parte, firſte, how God created vs all to ſerue him, &amp; to vſe all temporall thinges to his honour, and for releefe of our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, how there be two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſeruing God, and that we are all bounde to ſetue him in the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſorte.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly how by ſinn, we are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from godds fauour, into a miſerable ſtate both of body &amp; ſoule, the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of ſeruing God ſtill remaininge.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25031:34"/>
               <p>Fourthly how we may repaire again this calamitie and deſtruction in our ſoule, by the powers thereof, woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with godds grace: &amp; of the vſe of our vnderſtanding and will, to the ſame ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly to what ende you are to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all your actions, thoughts, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and how to doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, what way to extirpate euill and vitious habitts, which cauſe much harme in our ſoule, and how to plant the habitts of vertues.</p>
               <p>After we haue made collation, I ſhall inſtructe you, how to exercyſe your ſelf in a ſew principall thinges, which are neceſſary for the reparation of your ſoule, before you can be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed, to loue and ſerue God, in ſuch manner as he requireth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:34"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PARTE.</head>
            <head>THE SECOND PARTE, CON<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyning certayne ſperituall Exercyſes, wherby the ſoule is adorned, bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed, and rightlye diſpoſed to the perfect actes of louing &amp; ſeruinge God.</head>
            <div n="1" type="exercise">
               <head>THE first Exercyſe how the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God ſhoulde purge his ſoule from all ſinne.</head>
               <p>AFter they had refreſhed them ſelues with breade and water, which was the Ermits vſuall fair: he begann &amp; ſaide. My ſonn, the firſte thinge and Exercyſe, wherein a man muſte occupy him ſelfe, to gett a fitte diſpoſition, to loue and ſerue God, is to extirpate or roote owt of his ſoule, all euill, that is, the ſilthe of ſinne: that when he would do any ſeruice to his lord, there be nothinge that may offend the eyes of ſo highe a Maieſtie. This done, he muſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25031:35"/>and bewtify his ſoule with good habitts and vertues, whereby he may appeare gratefull &amp; acceptable to him in his ſeruice. Of theſe two thinges, I will therefore now ſpeake, and firſt how to roote owt and deſtroy ſinn.</p>
               <p>You muſt know then, that ſinne is the moſt vyle and deteſtable euill that can be deuyſed, &amp; bringethe to any reaſonable creature that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, vnſpeakable harmes and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheues. For by ſinn, we looſe God, who is an infinite goodnes. By it we contemne, diſhonour, and iniury, our louinge Lorde, in the fowleſt manner that may be. By it, we fruſtrate in oure ſelues, the effecte and frute, of Chriſts painfull lyfe, and moſte bitter paſſion, and conculcate or treade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote, his preceous blood. By it we defyle and make moſte lothſom &amp; abominable our owne ſoules, waſhed and ſanctifyed with the blood of oure Sauiour, and choſen to be the ſacred temples of Godds Maieſty. By it we pollute our harts, the Altars &amp; Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the holy Ghoſte, where he
<pb facs="tcp:25031:35"/>delightethe to dwell. By it we looſe godds fauour, and all his graces, the eternall ioyes of his kingdom, with all our right and tytle thereunto. By it onely we are made the boundſlaues of the deuill, the felowes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of all wicked men both aliue &amp; deade, &amp; of the damned ſpiritts in hell. By it, we are made the reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enemies of God, the moſte ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, contemptible, and diſhonorable of all his creatures. And finally by it we purchaſe aſſuredlye to our ſelues, endles damnation, eternall woes, and the horrible tormentes of hell fyre.</p>
               <p>All which euills and miſeries, are iuſtly dew to him, that by ſinn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth high treaſon againſte his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Lorde, who vouch-ſaifed to dye for him.</p>
               <p>Now the ſorowes and teares of all goddes creatures are not ſufficient to deſtroy or take away one ſinne: much leſſe the penance &amp; teares of one man that haith committed the ſame.</p>
               <p>But the mercy and clemency of oure Lord is ſo great, that he will not haue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25031:36"/>vs to diſpaire: And deſireous of our weale, haith prouided vs a remedie, &amp; is content to pardon &amp; forgeue our ſinns, aſſone as we for our parts, haue hartie ſorow &amp; contrition for the ſame: What beſides is needefull or requiſite, he ſupplieth it of his owne, &amp; reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs againe to his grace &amp; fauour. It is meete therefore that we lamente &amp; ſorow for out ſinnes, conſideringe we haue done ſo many euills by them both againſt God &amp; our ſelues.</p>
               <p>How ſhoulde we doe this as beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The way is this ſaid <hi>Alphouſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With your vnderſtandinge preſent to your ſelues, the cuills which come of ſinne as before: &amp; then compell your will (principally for the offence &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of God, and becauſe it is his will that you ſorowe for them) to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to deſyre that you had not committed them, nor iniuried godds maieſty: which acte of your will, you muſte often labour to produce; now in generall for all your ſinnes: now for one particular ſinn, now for an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:36"/>&amp; this with the greateſte ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour you can, to haue hartie greif and contrition, notwithſtanding you feele your ſelf ſomtimes voyde of ſenſible ſorowe or paine, for this is in godds hande and not in your owne, to haue at your pleaſure, but doubtleſſe he will beſtow it alſo on you, if you endeuour to gett it as you may.</p>
               <p>I vnderſtand all this ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then will I paſſe ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> to the ſecond thinge, which I tould you was requiſite, for the expellinge of our corruption &amp; euill habitts.</p>
               <p>What is that ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exercise">
               <head>THE SECONDE EXERCYSE neceſſarye for them that woulde ſerue God, which is the hatred of our felues.</head>
               <p>IT is the hatred of our ſelf ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo:</hi> And this Exercyſe amonge all other, is of greateſt weight and importance for them that deſyre per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to loue God and to ſerue him: For from ſelf loue, ſpringe innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25031:37"/>euills, by which are engendered viceous habitts: And this ſelf loue ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge at the entrance of that holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred (which the holy ſcriptures much exhort vs vnto) all ſinn will be deſtroy ed in vs, with all other wicked habits.</p>
               <p>How may we com to this holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of our ſelues ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſte ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> of all thinges which may bringe vs delectation and pleaſure, as meate, ſleepe, recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reſte, apparell, and the lyke, we muſt take or deſyre no more, then that we can not omitt or leaue vntaken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owt offence of god, that is, onely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries: And neceſſaries alſo muſte we take, not for our owne conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or for ſatiſfaction &amp; contentment of our owne appetites and ſenſualitie, conſideringe how vnworthy we be of all delectation, through the greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ſinnes: but onely for fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge godds holy will, who haith or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned &amp; appointed that we vſe and take ſuch thinges, to able vs more in his ſeruice, for which cauſe we admitt them willingly, for releefe of oure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities:
<pb facs="tcp:25031:37"/>otherwiſe we would notad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt them at all. What in theſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries is ſufficient, a mannes owne experience with a deuout mynd, will tell him.</p>
               <p>Secondly all thinges which be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; greuous, as laboures, toyles, abiections, contempts, iniuries, afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the lyke: We muſte take vnto vs, and deſyre or will they be done to vs as much as may be without offence of God, our owne or neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures harme.</p>
               <p>Thirdly if we would ſerue God, &amp; hate our ſelues in moſte commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, we muſt not onely refuſe delectable thinges, and deſyre pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; greuous as I ſaid: but more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we muſt ioy and be gladd, when any aduerſities or ſharpe things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto vs, &amp; when we are depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of pleaſant thinges, yea of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, &amp; this cheifly, when they are done by ſom others againſt our wills, or vpon euill intention: which yet we ought not to iudge withowt manifeſt ſignes, noe nor then neither with ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25031:38"/>&amp; full determination: but pray for our perſecutours, and loue them with all our hartes, becauſe in truthe they doe vs much good: &amp; otherwiſe we ſhoulde looſe the ineſtimable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde we are to receiue for ſuffering patiently perſecutions &amp; troubles.</p>
               <p>All theſe three thinges neceſſarye for the holy hatred of our ſelues, the Sonn of God taughte vs, both by his woord &amp; by his owne example, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith he ſuffered for vs,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2</note> leauinge vs an example to folowe his ſteppes, whoſe moſt bleſſed ſoule was free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſport of ſinne, &amp; therefore his holy body ſhould not haue bene entreated ſharply, or haue ſuffered any greua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at all: Yet woulde he for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he moſt tenderly loued) refuſe and ſet nothing by all delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinges, &amp; conſent that his body &amp; ſoule ſhould ſuffer excedinge tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; gretues, as it is manifeſt in his holy goſpell. Wherefore much ſhame &amp; reproch it is, to all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them ſelues to be Chriſtians and ſcholers of Chriſte, not to learne this
<pb facs="tcp:25031:38"/>holye hatred, neither by his woorde ſayinge: <hi>He that hatethe not him ſelfe, can not be my Diſciple:</hi> nor by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, but ſtande euer vnwillinge to ſuffer any payne or iniurye for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or to heare of it either.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> it is greate reproch &amp; diſhonour to a Chriſtian in this leſſon, to forſake &amp; not to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his Lord &amp; God, conſidering he ſuffered all for our ſakes &amp; inſtruction, and the commoditye of our laboures being all our owne. But what reaſons beſydes this can we conſider, why we ſhould thus hate our ſelues? For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe our willes be animated &amp; encora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by our vnderſtanding in this point, cheifly, which (for the naturall loue we beare to our ſelues) ſemeth terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; horrible to be thought vpon, we ſhall neuer deſire this hatred, much leſſe exercyſe our ſelues to gett it.</p>
               <p>The doctrine and example of our Sauiour ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> ſhould ſuffice, but I will geue you two or three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons moe. The firſt is, becauſe what ſoeuer euill is in vs, with all our want
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25031:39"/>of good &amp; vertues: all I ſay, comethe becauſe we hate not our ſelues, but loue and deſyre thinges either againſt the commaundement of God, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his counſells &amp; aduyſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſelf loue being ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to vs, and hatred of our ſelues ſo commodious, we haue good cauſe to deſyre &amp; labour for this later, and to flee that other.</p>
               <p>An other reaſon may be, becauſe by ſinning, we haue bene traitours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the maieſtie of God: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is meete &amp; iuſte, that we yelde him all poſſible ſatiſfaction. And ſeing that ſatiſfaction ſhoulde be anſweara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in greatnes, to the greuouſnes and malice of our ſinnes, &amp; we our ſelues can yelde but litle, and alſo in that we can doe, are verie negligent &amp; ſlack, to vſe our owne bodies hardly any way for making what ſatiſfaction we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: At the leaſt for this cauſe we ought to hate our ſelues as is declared, and to deſyre &amp; be ioyfull, that euery one hate, perſecute, &amp; afflict vs as much as they may without the offence of god
<pb facs="tcp:25031:39"/>that thus at the leaſte we may ſatiſfye vnto him, conſidering I ſay our own abilities otherwiſe ſuffice not.</p>
               <p>The third &amp; moſt high reaſon of all why we ſhould hate our ſelues is, that our ſoules being voyde &amp; emptie of ſelf loue, as farr forthe as may ſtande with Godds pleaſure: They may be filled with God him ſelf, whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in noe wyſe can ſuffer, that being emptie of ſelf loue, we ſhould not be filled with the loue of him, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently his holy will, reigne &amp; beare all ſway in oures. But of this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſon I ſhall tell you more, when we com to ſpeake of the loue of God.</p>
               <p>How ſhall we ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> vſe the inſtruments of our ſoule, to obteine this holye hatred of our ſelues?</p>
               <p>When we would ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe &amp; not admitt, thinges delectable &amp; pleaſant, or deſyre &amp; accept hard &amp; painefull things, as contempts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylinges, iniuryes, and the lyke: we muſt forgeat a litle theſe thinges, and not offer them thus nakedlye to oure will, but turne our mynde to conſider
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25031:40"/>the innumerable good thinges which com to vs, by refuſing the one ſort, &amp; accepting the other: And principally the infinyte treaſure of goddes loue, which we gett by hatred of our ſelues accordinge to his will. And then vpon theſe conſiderations, moue and inclyne our will to reiecte the pleaſant &amp; to embrace the greuous, as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie meanes to obteine theſe ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goods, euer with-all being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that you doe all this, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of your Lorde, and for fulfillinge his holy will &amp; pleaſure.</p>
               <p>But touching the ioyfull acceptance of paynefull thinges &amp; aduerſities: I ſhall tell you more, in the matters of Humilitie &amp; Patience.</p>
               <p>There is no more then to be learned ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for the hatred of our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Yes one thing more ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> which meruelouſly helpeth them that are deſireous to obteine this holie ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, which is, that continuallye and without ceaſing, we perſecute certain innumerable litle deſires of our owne, which if we marke, com runninge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb facs="tcp:25031:40"/>vs in euery moment, &amp; inclyne vs to ſelfe loue. Wherefore we muſt in all occaſions, be watchfull ouer our owne actions, &amp; verie circumſpectly marke, whether perhapps we deſire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which is not belonging vnto God, or not furtheringe vs towardes him: And incontinent ſo ſoone as we eſpye any thinge to delighte vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owt God, we muſt incline our will, to contradict &amp; refuſe it. And when we perceiue any thing to happen gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous &amp; diſpleaſant: We muſt by &amp; by, enclyne our will to couett &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it. If you be diligent in this, you ſhall both much ſooner gett this holy hatred, and withall ſuch dominion &amp; gouernment ouer your ſelf, as can not be expreſſed in woordes. Mark ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this well I ſay againe, &amp; exercyſe it, for aſſuredly this poynte is the key &amp; gate to cheife perfection.</p>
               <p>This hatred ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſeemethe contrary to Chatitie, whereby we are all bounde to loue our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Not ſo ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but ſo ſoone as a man hateth him ſelf in this ſort, &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25031:41"/>not before: he haith all the loue that he ought to haue towardes him ſelfe, &amp; which is moſt profitable &amp; glorious to him, and that which God woulde he ſhould haue. For then haith he the loue of God, of vertues, of eternall glory, and of all thinges which helpe him thither, which loue doth not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with it the company of any vyce.</p>
               <p>But now let vs goe to the ſeconde thinge, that is, to know how we may adorne &amp; bewtify our ſoules with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. As it pleaſeth you ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exercise">
               <head>THE THIRD EXERCYSE. How the ſeruant of God, ſhould behaue him ſelfe in prayer.</head>
               <p>YOu muſte know therefore ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that he is ſaid to haue his ſoule adorned &amp; bewtifyed, that haith his naturall appetites confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable with his reaſon and godds will &amp; Law. And this conformity is none other thing, but a certain heap of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which placed orderly in the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:25031:41"/>make it bewtifull, and directe it as is conuenient for the great dignity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, mitigating &amp; repreſſing, all falſe and euill concupiſcenſes, which had ſtook in the ſoule by ſinne, &amp; diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to ſerue, &amp; withowt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, to yeld gratefull obeiſance to the will of him that created it.</p>
               <p>And becauſe our owne ſtrength &amp; powers, are verie weake &amp; vnable to obteyne ſuche thinges: I will reache you firſte, how to call for helpe from God by prayer. Secondly, howe by many particularactes: you muſt build theſe habitts of vertues, ſpeakinge of ſom few which be principall. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how you muſt ſubdue &amp; keepe in ſemely order, your foure naturall paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Ioy, Sorow, Hope, &amp; Feare.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OF PRAIER.</head>
                  <p>FOr Praier then, you muſte know that Goddes pleaſure is, that we ſtande neede of his ſupernaturall help, becauſe the ende &amp; felicity whereto he haithe created vs, is ſupernaturall,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25031:42"/>that is the bliſſe of heauen. His will alſo is, that we aſke &amp; demande it of him, not, but that he deſyrethe more to geue it vs, then we to take or aſke it: But firſt that we may poſſeſſe and enioy the thing with more honoure, which we get with greater endeuoure &amp; labour in ſuting for it, &amp; that we may as it were meritt the ſame: And ſecondly, that as importune beggers, we may the oftner preſente our ſelues before him, and ſo come into more knowledg of his Maieſties greatnes, preheminence, &amp; perfections, &amp; more ioy in him, and loue him with a true knowledg &amp; contempt of all thinges, which either are not God, or not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering to him, &amp; finally, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue of vertue, and an hatred of all ſinn. By which our neceſſitye of praying to him, he keepe the vs with him as with a pledge: For vnleſſe we ſtoode euer in nede of him, we ſhould quickly without doubt, forgeat him.</p>
                  <p>To preſent our ſelues often before our Lord by prayer ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> muſt needes bring to vs, many good things
<pb facs="tcp:25031:42"/>you ſay: But in what ſorte may oure prayer be acceptable to god, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to our ſelues?</p>
                  <p>That our prayer ſaid <hi>Alpho ſo,</hi> may be gratefull in Godds ſight, merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; effectuall, it is not ſo muche needefull, that the thing we aſke, be of great valewe, as that in our prayer we haue an high motiue or ende. For if his motiue that praieth for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, and his that aſke the breade to eate, or health of his body, be all one or equall: their paayers be of equall meritt, not-withſtandinge the things they pray for, farr excede, the one the other.</p>
                  <p>What motiue &amp; ende ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſhould we haue, to make our prayer moſt excellent &amp; acceptable?</p>
                  <p>We ſhould aſke or pray for euery thinge ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> becauſe it is Godds bleſſed will that we aſke and haue it by prayer, and that obteyning it, we may be more diſpoſed, &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abled, to loue &amp; ſerue him.</p>
                  <p>Thus the prayer for breade, or any other meane thinge, is of excellente
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25031:43"/>meritt, &amp; ſo diſpoſed ſhould we be in our harts, when we come to prayer, that if we thought it diſpleaſing or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull to God, for vs to haue the thinge: we would forthwith, neither defire nor aſke it. The hungry man comonly is moued to pray for bread, in releef of his neceſſitie: but the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of god that rightly praieth, ought not to aſke meate, vertues, grace, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or any other thing, for his owne neceſſitie or benefyte, but for fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the will of his Lorde, who much deſireth that he haue them, expecting onelye his petition, that he may geue them: ſo that the will of god (deſirig that I haue the good I aſke, &amp; that I pray for it, &amp; that by it I may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed to ſerue him) muſt more moue me to deſire &amp; pray for it: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie ioy or good I looke for thereby.</p>
                  <p>May we not ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> pray for Grace, vertues, forgeuenes of oure ſinnes, the ioyes of heauen, or other good thinges, for ſome other good end beſides this? A praeir ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo,</hi> may be deuout &amp; good, which is
<pb facs="tcp:25031:43"/>for any good or indifferent thing, to a good end, but there is none ende or motiue, which can make it ſo perfect and acceptable as this, in which I am moued to pray onely for the loue of God, &amp; for fulfilling his bleſſed will &amp; pleaſure, and not vpon any loue to my ſelf, or to the thinge I aſke, or for any other reſpect. And yet may we in our prayers for this ende, kepe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a loue, to the good thing we aſke &amp; wiſhe to our ſelues alſo with greate perfection &amp; meritt: ſo that we actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye referr it thus, that therefore we loue the thing and wiſh it, becauſe it is godds will we loue it, and defire to haue it. And ſo we make God, and neither the thing nor our ſelues, the ende of our prayer.</p>
                  <p>I will geue you an example of this ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> againe, and withall let you ſee, how to vſe your will rightly in praying.</p>
                  <p>A man may aſke any thinge of his frend, either for the loue he bearethe to it, or for his own commoditie, or for the loue of his frende: Vſuallye
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25031:44"/>men aſke it for their owne good and benefite, &amp; not for the loue of their frend. Now the ſeruant of god ſhould refuſe with his will to aſke any thing, for the loue he beareth to the thinge or for his own commoditie: and aſk it onely for the loue of his Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſeth his Maieſtie that he aſke &amp; haue it, that he may ſerue and pleaſe him the more: As he that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for pardon &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſinns, &amp; ſoroweth for them, ſhould doe it more, becauſe he ſeethe that to be in his ſoule which offendeth God, &amp; for a deſire he haith to haue it pure, that ſo he may yelde gratefull &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice to his Lord: Then for any feare of puniſhmente or other harme or loſſe to him ſelf whatſoeuer. And againe, as he that prayethe to eſcape tribulations, ought to feele in his hart a deſire, &amp; accordingly to pray to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape them, not cheefly for auoyding daunger, harme, or trouble: but for that tribulations may be to him, an impediment to ſerue God, carryinge euer withall, an vnfeaned deſire and
<pb facs="tcp:25031:44"/>will, that godds bleſſed will be done therein, if at any tyme it pleaſe him to be ſerued by his troubles &amp; paines. And ſo finallye in aſkinge any other good, that we aſke it, not for oure owne conſolation, but that hauinge it, we may thereby be more ſtirred vp &amp; furthered to ſerue and loue God.</p>
                  <p>It will ſeme eaſie to you, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I tould you before co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the vſe of your will, and the ende that you ſhoulde haue in doinge all thinges: &amp; the example I gaue you then, of him that regardinge more his frendes neceſſitie then his owne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him the medicyne, which he prouyded for him ſelfe, will ſerue here alſo.</p>
                  <p>I remember well ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> what you ſaid there.</p>
                  <p>Remember it ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> &amp; be diligent to produce according to thoſe inſtructions, many actes: and in ſhorte tyme, you will fynde greate ſweetnes to pray vpon this motiue, thoughe in the beginning, you ſeeme to be drye or without comforthe and deuotion,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25031:45"/>hapneth, becauſe you leaue your own ſelf loue, which euer moued you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to pray. But Godds loue increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge in you: deuotion and ſweetnes with exceding great meritt, will alſo increaſe.</p>
                  <p>See therefore you paſſe not from aſking one thinge, to aſke an other, before you firſte inclyne your will to aſke it, becauſe God would haue you to aſke it, &amp; that you inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſerue him by aſkinge it.</p>
                  <p>I vnderſtande all this ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you ſo doe ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> then may we ſpeake of getting vertues for adorning our ſoules.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exercise">
               <head>THE FOVRTH EXERCYSE. How to gett the vertue of Humilitye, which is one of them, that oure Sauioure willed vs to learne of him ſelfe.</head>
               <p>ALL vertues ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> may beſt be redd, &amp; learned in the booke of lyſe, &amp; fountayne of wiſdom our Sauiour Chirſt. And let
<pb facs="tcp:25031:45"/>none hope nor think they can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with vertues, vnleſſe they learn them of the Sonn of God made man, &amp; principally of his ſacred paſſion, for this is geuen vnto the world by the Father of heauen, as a moſte plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gould-myne, that owt of it we may gather all treaſures, ſee &amp; heare the excellency of euery vertue.</p>
               <p>Therefore happy is he that by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall meditation, entrethe into the hidden &amp; inner ſecretts of this myne: for there he ſhall finde ſtoared vppe, all the treaſures of God.</p>
               <p>What vertues ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> will he that we firſt learne of him?</p>
               <p>He haith willed vs ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> to learne of him ſelf two, which are, Humilitie, &amp; Patience, ſaying, <hi>Learu of me, that I am patient, and humble of harte:</hi> which two, when we haue learned: we ſhall be full of true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and not before. Of theſe two therefore, I will tell you howe they may be gotten.</p>
               <p>Many haue writen of the ſtepps &amp; degrees of Humilitie, for it is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25031:46"/>which reacheth verie high, &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth verie low: &amp; without ſtepps let no man hope to clyme to the topp thereof: but he that once arryue the thither, ſhall preſently come into ſuch knowledg of himſelf, &amp; all thinges: that thereby he ſhall moſt clearly ſee how of him ſelf, he is and haith vetie nothinge, and that onely God is the thing, that trulie is. For which cauſe he deſireth that all the thoughtes and powers of men be bente to praiſe &amp; magnifye him onely, whoſe is euery thing that is. Moreouer he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (becauſe Humilitie coueteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more then is it owne) that the whole world entreate &amp; eſteme him as he is, that is for nothinge: And that menns harts be not occupyed, yea for any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle moment, in eſteming that to be of ſome worth, which in truth is nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or a veſſell of iniquitie which is worſe then nothing, as euery ſinner is.</p>
               <p>Herein therefore conſiſteth the key of Humilitie, that this which I haue now ſaid, may be fixed in our hartes, by many actes of good conſideration:
<pb facs="tcp:25031:46"/>couetinge with-all, that they which harme or diſpyſe vs, &amp; that they alſo which ſee it, may thinke vs to ſuffer, not vpon humilitye, but becauſe we can not otherwyſe doe, as S. <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture</hi> ſaith, that he which laboreth to pleaſe God, muſte endeuour to be thought vyle &amp; abiecte, not humble and modeſt.</p>
               <p>Me think ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> it were good to ſhew our Humilitye to others, for their edification.</p>
               <p>If a man ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> were of ſuch perfect vertue, that without any repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or difficulty, he could wiſhe to be eſtemed of all men vyle, abiect, &amp; nothing, as I ſaid before: ſuche a one might deſire, for the edification of his neighboures, that they ſhould think him to ſuffer iniuries willingly, &amp; with ioy, for the loue of God and humilitie, &amp; this were heroycall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, which was moſte perfecte in our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>I pray you Father ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to me the humilitie of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure, ſeinge I muſte haue it before
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25031:47"/>myne eyes as a patern to imitate.</p>
               <p>The humility of our Sauiour ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> conteyneth in it, moſt high &amp; vnſpeakable miſteries, &amp; better may all creatures admire it, then com nigh in folowing it. For our Sauiour being God omnipotente, of infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and a moſte perfecte man, did chooſe &amp; will with great ioy, to be eſtemed for a moſt meane thing, yea almoſt for nothing, &amp; for ſuch a one he would be hardly intreated with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, contumelies, reproches, &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, from the firſt day of his birth till he ſuffred a moſt ſharpe &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deathe. All which he did, not for that they weare needefull for him ſelf: but that we who haue great neede thereof, mighte learne the manner of humbling our ſelues by his example.</p>
               <p>Now the ſeruant of God muſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; doe his beſt endeuour, to frame his humilitie, like to this of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours: that is, conſideringe his owne vylenes, abiection, and vnworthines, he ought to couet &amp; deſire, with great ioy (I ſay againe with greate ioy, for
<pb facs="tcp:25031:47"/>for this is the pith of all) that in the eyes &amp; hartes of all men, he be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as worthleſſe, and accordingly to be intreated, for of our ſelues we are none other, nor deſerue better. This is the humilitie which oure Sauioure would haue vs to learne of him.</p>
               <p>Why doth God ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre of vs ſo great humilitie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of our ſelues; &amp; why would he teach it vs with ſo great coſt &amp; harme to him ſelf?</p>
               <p>He requyreth it of vs ſaid <hi>Alphonſo</hi> becauſe in truth it is conuenient for vs, &amp; becauſe that of our ſelues we haue no good, nor deſerue any at all, thoe we receiue many good thinges from the magnificall hande of God, from whom we ought to acknowledge to haue receiued them, &amp; therefore glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him &amp; not our ſelues. Againe he requyreth it, becauſe it (beinge vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily taken) is the perfecte medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyne of our mortall infirmitie, which cometh by pryde. Neither ſhall any man euer be ſoundly cured of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, withowt perfecte humilitie.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:25031:48"/>
               <p>And the more we wante of perfect curinge, the more alſo we ſhall wante of the puritie of our ſoule: &amp; the more we wante of the puritie of our ſoule, the more ſhall we want of godds gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; benefites, and ſo much the leſſe ſhall we be his. Now that he woulde teach it vs with ſo much harme to him ſelf, proceded from his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; from his moſt tender &amp; inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable loue to vs, not appointing men, or Angells to this office, but deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſelf to be our inſtructour and guyde, notwithſtandinge any harmes or inconueniences, that mighte befall him therefore.</p>
               <p>How may we ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> come to gett this Humilitie, and to reioyce in contempts, iniuries, &amp; tribulations, for it is verie hard to deſire theſe thinges?</p>
               <p>We may obteyne all this, ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> by much conſidering the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie of godds Sonn, which I toulde you of before, &amp; the profitt that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to our ſelues by it: &amp; cheefely becauſe we are ſo abled &amp; made fitt, to yelde acceptable ſeruice vnto God,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:48"/>and to pleaſe him. Wherefore we muſt verie often inclyne our willes, to couet and with ioy deſire, abiections, contempts, and iniuries, which are ſo preceous &amp; ſo profitable.</p>
               <p>O how deſeruedly oughte he to be humbled, or to be humble, &amp; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be deſpyſed, that ſo often haith bene traiterous againſt his eternall lord yelding his ſoule to the deuill by ſinn, &amp; taking it from god, that ſo louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dyed for it. Surely if we would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlye marke this, we ſhould receiue honoures (if at anie tyme they were offred vs) with much greife, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering they hinder vs of the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodes which we might gett by i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating &amp; accompanying the Kinge of heauen, in contempts, diſhonoures, contumelies, &amp; the lyke.</p>
               <p>May not a man with humilitie ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> deſire ſomtimes to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; honored?</p>
               <p>Yes ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> he may deſire this in ſome caſes, as when (without reſpect of his own eſtimation) he haith his eye, reſpect, &amp; intention onely to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25031:49"/>ſome ſeruice, &amp; honour which he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, may redownde to god thereby.</p>
               <p>But in this caſe alſo he ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſuch eſtimation with feare and ſom ſorow, that he muſt be honored, &amp; with great circumſpection, that he be not deceiued with ſelf loue.</p>
               <p>How may I know ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch caſe as this I kepe humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, with that deſire of honour?</p>
               <p>You may know &amp; diſcerne this ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> if you ioy noe whitt in that eſtimation &amp; honour, but onely in the ſeruice &amp; honour which is done to god by it. And again, if you fele in your hart an vnfeaned deſire or diſpoſition, that leauing all honour &amp; eſtimation (if ſo it might pleaſe God) you had rather for your owne part, choſe to yeld him your ſeruice, by ſuffering contempts, diſpyſinges, diſgraces, &amp; iniuries, then by that eſtimation, credit, &amp; honour.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, if you fynde your hart as deſireous &amp; ioyfull, that other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be eſtemed &amp; honored for the ſeruice &amp; honour of God, as your ſelf, or that they be preferred before you: without
<pb facs="tcp:25031:49"/>any emulation.</p>
               <p>When a man ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> haithe receiued benefites &amp; good gifts from God, why may he not delight &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in them?</p>
               <p>He may ioy &amp; delight in them ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> ſo he kepe humilitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, &amp; fall not into vayne-glorye: for otherwyſe he ſhoulde turne all gods gifts to his diſhonour, &amp; his own gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ruyne. I muſt therefore by the way, geue you warning of vayn-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is a vyce that defileth &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyethe, all our vertues and good deedes, vnleſſe we auoyde it well.</p>
               <p>I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> teach me to eſcape it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exercise">
               <head>THE FIFTH EXERCYSE. HOW to ouercom the vyce of vainglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is a mortall enemye to Humilitie &amp; all vertue.</head>
               <p>VAin-glorie ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is the Mother of all euill, &amp; it aboue all other thinges, hindreth the increaſe of Humilitie. It is a complacency or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25031:50"/>delight &amp; ioy, which one taketh of ſome thing he ought not, or in ſome ſort as he ought not. And there be diuers kyndes of it: As firſte a man may glory &amp; reioyce for his own wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked factes &amp; euill deedes. This kind of glory &amp; ioye, is not amonge Gods children and ſeruantes, but proper to graceles &amp; moſt wicked perſons, and therefore I will lett it paſſe.</p>
               <p>Againe one may glory and ioy for ſome good thinge or gifte which he haith not: This alſo is moſt fooliſhe, vaine, &amp; ridiculous, yet is it often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the good, as ordinary to the badd, procedinge from a diſordered ſelf loue, &amp; a prowde mynde, deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in it owne prayſe &amp; flaterye.</p>
               <p>Againe, one may glory &amp; reioyce vainelye, for ſome good he haith or doth, or heareth of him ſelf: This is that kynde, which aſſaultethe muche godds ſeruantes. Nowe a man may well ioye in the gifes which he haith of God, ſo farr forth as he ſeethe and hopeth thereby, ſome ſeruice to God or profitt to his owne ſoule. For God
<pb facs="tcp:25031:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>haith left it in our owne liberty, that we may ſo much ioy for euery good gift of God, as we know it to be from God, &amp; to redownd to gods honour &amp; ſeruice: But when it once paſſeth this ordinance appointed by god, by &amp; by it becometh vain-glory, or vain ioy excedinge the limitts appoynted by God, as glorying and reioycinge in our ſelues, where we ſhould glory onely in God.</p>
               <p>How may we diſcern ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> when our glorye &amp; ioye is vayne, or true &amp; ſpirituall as it ſhould be?</p>
               <p>This vain-glorie ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is ſo deceyptfull and ſubtill: that one yet a nouice &amp; weake in vertue, may often thinke him ſelf to ioye in God for the good he haith, and neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe much vain-glorie is mixed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Wherefore till a man euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, &amp; haue throughly tryed ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to be in him ſelf, he ſhoulde euer flee all kynd of ioy and complacency whyles he calleth to mynd the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites that he haith receiued from God or the good giftes he haith or heareth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25031:51"/>ſpoken of him ſelf, and rather accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom his harte to motions of feare, at theſe tymes, as ſuſpecting vain glorie which verye ſecretly vſethe to creepe vpon vs in ſuch occaſions. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ought to ſuſpect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> think it vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorie &amp; ioy which he haith of godds gifts geuen him: ſo long as he haith not as much ioy &amp; glorye in the gifts &amp; benefites, which he knoweth other men to haue receiued from god, as he haith of his own. For albeit we ought to deſire and chooſe vertues for oure ſelues, before other, &amp; alſo to ioy that (ſeing it is godds will and ordinance that bothe we &amp; others ſhoulde haue them) it haith pleaſed him to beſtow them vpon vs: Yet when both we &amp; they, haue receiued gifts from godds bountifull hande, ſeing god him ſelf equally ioyeth in both: our ioy &amp; glory in lyke forte, oughte to be equall for them both in God onely, &amp; that his bleſſed will is fulfilled.</p>
               <p>I vnderſtand this ſatd <hi>Probus:</hi> but teach me I pray you, how I may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde this fowle ſinne of vain-glory,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:51"/>and vaine ioy.</p>
               <p>You may ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> by the vſe of your vnderſtanding &amp; will, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com it, &amp; eſcape all the daunger ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For by the aſſiſtance of gods grace you can hate that, which you once know to be vaine &amp; falſe. Conſider therefore the vanitie &amp; falſed thereof by this example or compariſon.</p>
               <p>You will confeſſe it to be a fowle thinge, if ſome courtier would eſteme it for a matter of great valew or worth or would glory in his harte, that he had offred him ſelf to a litle daunger for the ſeruice &amp; loue of his Prince, who had yelded him ſelf before, to moſt greuous torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; cruell wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for the courtiers ſake &amp; cauſe.</p>
               <p>But if the ſame courtier, did not onelye in his owne conceipte, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteeme that litle he had done for his Prince, to whom he was ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly bound &amp; behoulden: but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer before others, woulde prowdly vaunt him ſelfe thereof: it were moſt ridiculous, to-too groſſe follie, intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pryde &amp; leuitie: Yet were it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25031:52"/>more abominable vanitye by farr, if that Prince had ſuffred all his torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; woundes voluntarily &amp; without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny comforth or ſuccour of his courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but the courtier contrari-wiſe, had ſuffered his litle with great fauour, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, &amp; comforth, of the Prince, &amp; hauing promiſe alſo before his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, of great benefites &amp; rewards, &amp; receiued the ſame afterwards: So in like manner he falleth into noe leſſe abominable vanitie, yea &amp; into worſe incomparablye, that folowethe after vain-glory. For our high God, and King of incomprehenſible Maieſtie, of infinite power &amp; honour, through his owne goodnes onely withowt any bounde, behoulding our extreme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, for our ſakes and ſaifties, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him ſelf, to a moſt ſharpe and ignominious death: In which we not onelye gaue him noe comforthe nor ſuccoure, but more-ouer we yelded him noe thankes, yea all that were with him, fledd &amp; forſooke him: &amp; we alſo more forſake him now through defect of our vertue, when his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:52"/>mercy, and goodnes, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted vnto vs. Which thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge thus, let vs acknowledge how vayne it is for any man to glory for his ſeruice he doth to God, omitting in the meane ſeaſon, to glory &amp; ioye in god onely. And moreouer let vs conſider how exceding vaine it is, to deſire for this ſmal ſeruice, to be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtemed with others, whereas for that tyme whiles their hartes are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, in iudginge vs to be of ſome worth, they ceaſe to be occupyed in worthily eſteming &amp; prayſinge God, of whom we haue, &amp; whoſe is, all our good.</p>
               <p>God forbidd, that the hart which is not occupyed in highly eſteming &amp; praiſing God, to whom all prayſe is due, ſhoulde be occupyed in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any worth, to whom noe ſuch thing is due. And he alſo deſerueth much blame for his conſentinge, that thinketh other to occupy their hartes, in praiſing &amp; eſteming him beinge ſo vyle &amp; abiect, ſeaſinge in that meane tyme to magnify god for all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25031:53"/>&amp; giftes, &amp; is not aſhamed nor greued, for ſo great diſorder &amp; abuſe of thinges. It augmenteth alſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our vanitie, that whatſoeuer we do, or ſuffer, all is by the mighty grace &amp; help of our moſt high God. It is ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> a thing both glorious &amp; meritorious, that we accept the gifts &amp; graces of God, &amp; not reiect or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them: and then why may we not glorie &amp; think well of our ſelues that we accepted them? We neuer ſaw man ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that would vainly glory &amp; boaſte, onely becauſe he had accepted benefites, done him by a Prince, but rather it would haue bene iudged playne madnes, to haue refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And it is great folly for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to glorye and boaſte, that he would not be madd whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he might, or proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to behaue and eſteme him ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not leap into a pitt &amp; drowne him ſelf when he might haue done it. Muche leſſe cauſe ſurelye haith any man to glorye, becauſe he accepted godds giftes &amp; refuſed them not, conſidering that their verye ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptinge
<pb facs="tcp:25031:53"/>and will to receiue them, is not done by their own power &amp; abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or nature,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4</note> but principally by the grace and helpe of God, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: <hi>What haſt thou that thou haſte not receyued? &amp; if thou haſte receiued it, why doeſt thou glory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe after your vnderſtandinge haith had theſe &amp; ſuch lyke conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of this vyce: moue &amp; incline your will as I taughte you before, to refuſe &amp; hate it: And ſtanding firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the true conceipte of your owne baſenes &amp; vnworthines, yeld all praiſe &amp; glory to God to whom it is due, &amp; in him onely, let all your ioye and glory be, &amp; reſt.</p>
               <p>The actions of your will, you muſt diligently vſe in all occaſions, where this vain-glorie would creepe in, and draw you to delighte in your ſelf, or in any thing you haue. This may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce concerning the euill vyce of vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory. Now will we ſpeake of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is the ſeconde vertue we are to learne of our Sauiour Chriſte, vnleſſe you teſte vnſatiſfyed in ſome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25031:54"/>thing I haue ſaid.</p>
               <p>Goe forwarde ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> I pray you, for I vnderſtande you well, and haue nothing to replye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exercise">
               <head>THE SIXT EXERCYSE. HOW to plant in our ſoules, the vertue of Patience, which is one of the two vertues, which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our would haue vs to learn of him.</head>
               <p>PAtience ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is ſo dear a ſiſter &amp; companion to Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that comonly they are found together: And by what waies &amp; paths the one is found, you may finde the other alſo. And as we ſaid before that to gett Humilitie, it is neceſſarie we ſett before our eyes, the humilitie of godds Sonne: ſo muſte we doe alſo the ſame here, for obteyninge this vertue of Patience. For who can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine or repyne inſufferinge iniuries, or any tribulation (hauinge deſerued them as we all haue) when he conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with how great mildnes and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:54"/>his Lorde god voluntarily did chooſe to ſuffer ſo manie &amp; ſo greate iniuries, contumelies, perſecutions, &amp; tormentes, together with a moſte bitter death: who (beſides that he was true God &amp; Lord of all) was alſo a man of more noble, delicate, &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der complexion, then any other man in the world, &amp; more feelinge, anie affliction.</p>
               <p>Who will not patiently &amp; myldly ſuſtain for curing his owne ſinnes, a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie toyle, vexation, or diſtreſſe that may befall: if he conſider his God to haue ſuſteyned farr greater for the ſinns of other, &amp; to bringe remedy to our euills.</p>
               <p>The example of our Sauioure ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſhould indede moue &amp; ſuffice vs to take anie aduerſitie patientlye: but our frayle natures, can not away with trouble or affliction.</p>
               <p>Naturallye indeede ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> we are inclyned to flee &amp; abhorr the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But godds grace preuenting our wills &amp; cooperatinge with vs, we may be brought in ſhort tyme, to accept and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25031:55"/>embrace them, and this the rather, if we conſider, not onely this example which our Sauiour haith geuen vs, but more-ouer caſt our eye, to the great commoditie we gett thereby, which our Lorde alſo is deſireous we labour to obteine.</p>
               <p>For perſecutions &amp; tribulations, are as it were a hammer or fire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ruſt or canker of our ſoules is taken away: or as a launcinge knife, thruſt into our ſoules, to let owt the poyſen of our ſelf loue, which feſtreth there &amp; drawethe vs from all good; that once freed from that filthe, we may woorke the high woork of God, that is, loue &amp; ſerue him as we ſhould.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe, we ought hartely to loue &amp; pray for our perſecutours, &amp; thank God that prouideth vs ſo good ſurgeons.</p>
               <p>Teache me the way ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> I pray you, to gett this vertue.</p>
               <p>If you remember ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>P. C.</hi> 7.</note> I taught it you before, when we talked of the way, how to plant vertuous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits in our ſoule. For there I put the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="tcp:25031:55"/>of Patience, which may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice alſo for this place.</p>
               <p>I remember it verie well ſaid <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That alſo which I taughte you ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> of the hatred of your ſelfe,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Part.</hi> 2 <hi>Exer.</hi>
                  </note> you muſt call to mynde againe in this mater, for the reaſons I gaue you why you ſhould hate your ſelf, may ſerue fitlye, to moue you to ſuffer patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any aduerſitie or affliction. Now let vs propounde one example of ſom odious matter, that may befall.</p>
               <p>You either ſuſpect or certenly know a man to ſpeak or reporte ſom euill of you, which you neuer committed.</p>
               <p>Hereby three dartes are caſte at you to wound your ſoule: from all which the ſouldier and ſeruant of God, muſt cleare &amp; acquyte him ſelf, that by his fight, his Lorde may be ſerued &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, and his owne ſoule bewtified.</p>
               <p>The firſt is the dart of euill ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or iudgment, againſte the man, or againſt his intention. From this dart you muſt withdraw your ſelf, and let it paſſe, inclyninge your will, not to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25031:56"/>accept or deale with it, as conſenting to any ſuch ſuſpition or iudgment, but to referr it wholly vnto God, who is the high Iudg of all, and haith willed vs not to iudge. For fulfilling of whoſe will, we ought with great ioy to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to iudge, and not to vſurpe or cake vpon vs his office.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the darte of greuous impatiencye; To this you muſte op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your ſelf with all your ſtrengthe, ioying in the paine and iniury, which cometh to you by that occaſion, and the more you ſeme to ioye of it, the leſſe will the deuill aſſaulte you with impatience, leſt he geue you occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo great meritt.</p>
               <p>That you may well demeane your ſelfe in receiuing this dart, remember what I ſaid of the hatred of your ſelf.</p>
               <p>The third is the dart of hatred, of him whom you ſuſpecte or know, to haue done you wronge. To this alſo you muſt oppoſe your ſelf, inclyninge your will, to produce ſome ſingular acte of loue towards him, becauſe it is godds will, that you loue and pray
<pb facs="tcp:25031:56"/>for your enemies. And in truth as I ſaid, they doe you exceding greate good, if your ſelf hinder it not, and they be as ſurgeons, to cure the feſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring woundes of our ſoule.</p>
               <p>Thus in all occaſions of aduerſitie, the ſeruant of God ſhould be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and euer ſtand prepared patiently to endure, what-ſoeuer it pleaſethe his Lorde to let befall for his tryall, that in ſo doing, he may honoure his Lord, benefite, and (as our Sauioure ſaid) poſſeſſe his own ſoule, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth as voyd of all good, captiue to the deuill, and quite loſte, if it be ſpoyled of this vertue of patience.</p>
               <p>Nowe if you thinke good, let vs ſpeake of the foure affections or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="exercise">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:25031:57"/>
               <head>THE SEAVENTH EXERCYSE. HOW to moderate and keepe in order, the foure naturall paſſions of the ſoule.</head>
               <p>THeſe paſſions ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> be Ioy, Sorow, Hope, &amp; Feare: &amp; they be naturall to euery one, as to ioy for a preſente good, to ſorowe for a preſent euill, to hope for a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good, and to feare a future euill.</p>
               <p>I will teach you how to guyde and brydle them conueniently for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and honour of God, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payringe of your ſoule. For they may bringe vs much harme if they be lefte at libertie vnreſtrayned, becauſe they neuer ceaſe ranginge vpp and downe in our ſoules, now one, now an other.</p>
               <p>And we may well ſay, that all our euills come vpon vs, becauſe they are permitted, to wander abowte, and runne vnbrydled. Yea they bringe much annoyance and hurte to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall perſons, howe lightlye ſoeuer they walke in them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:57"/>
               <p>He onely may kepe them in good order &amp; great moderation, that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all thnges, aſwell internal as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, for God, as I toulde you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; walketh in the hatred of him ſelf, as you haue harde.</p>
               <p>When are theſe affections ſaid <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> kept in due order &amp; moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
               <p>When we yelde ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> no conſent to any of their motions, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we know pleaſeth God, &amp; whereby he may receiue ſome grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice: Otherwyſe, we oughte euer to repell their motions &amp; baniſh them from vs, if we deſire to walke a ſaife way towarde God.</p>
               <p>May we not ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> be glad and ioyfull for any good thinge that hapneth vnto vs, &amp; in lyke ſorte be ſorowfull for euill?</p>
               <p>The ſeruants of God ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> ſhould be gladd &amp; ioy in nothing but God, or thinges which belong or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect &amp; further them to him. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, for that hauinge in God, &amp; in ſuch thinges, ſo great cauſe &amp; matter of ioyes: they are verye fooliſhe and madd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25031:58"/>vaine, that occupye them ſelues, in ioying for any other, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering their powers &amp; force to ioy in God &amp; loue him, are the weaker, by how muche more they are deuyded, into dyuers ioyes &amp; buſines. And conſideringe againe, that albeit we yelde our ſelues wholly to ioy in God, yet are we not able to doe it ſufficiently: How much leſſe can we doe it, if we diſtract our ſelues to ioy in many thinges?</p>
               <p>Wherefore by the vſe &amp; power of our will, as I toulde you before, we muſt doe one of theſe two, either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſo ſone as it offereth it ſelf, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell &amp; putt away all ioye and gladnes which is not in God, or thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longinge vnto him: or direct &amp; order it for God, as the ende thereof, ſo it be not ſome vaine or vnlawfull ioye.</p>
               <p>And thus ſhall we doe as the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle willeth vs ſaying:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4</note> 
                  <hi>Ioy in our Lorde at all tymes: I ſay againe, ioye.</hi> For he which cauſe, we muſt looke warelye about vs, for daily innumerable things of ſmall weight, occurre &amp; ofter them ſelues to vs, bringinge occaſions and
<pb facs="tcp:25031:58"/>cauſes of ioy &amp; gladnes: from which forth-with we ought to vnwynde our ſelues, knowinge all ioyes which are offered vnto vs by the world, are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured harmes, &amp; noe good to vs at all.</p>
               <p>In a moſt potent and ryche King, you know it would be iudged, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry baſe &amp; vyle diſpoſition, to make ſo greate reckning of a peny, that the winning of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> woulde make him verie ioyfull, &amp; the looſing of it, verie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull &amp; greiued: But farr greater is our baſenes &amp; vilitye, if when alwaies we haue preſent, the infinite goodes which God poſſeſſeth for him ſelf &amp; vs, in which we oughte inceſſantly to ioye: we turne our ſelues to ioy in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tryflinge thinges which occurr in the world, when eſpecially we ought to loue our Lord more then our ſelues, &amp; more to reſpect his glory then our owne, which yet he will geue vs moſt aboundantlye, if we faithfully and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerelye ſerue him, in this our baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:25031:59"/>
                  <head>OF SOROW.</head>
                  <p>IN lyke ſort may we ſpeake of him that ſoroweth for any thing of this world that may happen, except ſin &amp; things inducing thereto. For it may be well iudged great baſenes, to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for any ſuch temporall thinge of this lyfe, whearas we haue before oure eyes, ſo great glorye and ineſtimable goodes as I ſaid God haith prouided for vs, for which we ought euer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce &amp; be gladd. Wherefore the ſeruant of God, muſte ſuffer noe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row nor heauines to ſtay in his harte, but that onely which is for ſinn: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſorow being a paſſion which reſpecteth ſome preſent euill, or ſome good loſt, &amp; true euills &amp; loſſes can not happen, but onely for ſinne: He ought with reaſon to ſorowe for none other thinge. And hauing preſent ſo infinite an euill to ſorowe for as ſinne is: he doth moſt fooliſhlye, if deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his force &amp; ſtrength, he ſorowe for any other thing beſides, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eſpecially, that all his powers &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25031:59"/>abilities collected to this one woork, ſuffice not to ſorow ſo much for ſinn, as he ſhould doe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſorowes which offer them ſelues dailie to vs vpon any tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or aduerſitie, we may eaſily repell, if we conſider, that we be gods more then our owne, &amp; that he haith more tender care ouer vs, then we can haue of oure ſelues, and beſte knowethe what is expedient for vs. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what painefull thing or aduerſity ſoeuer hapneth, it ought to be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com to vs, ſo long as it endureth, &amp; we muſt take it ioyfullye as from the hande of our louinge Lorde, and as a thinge fitt and conuenient for one that is godds, &amp; ſorow no more for it, then God (whoſe we are) willeth that we ſorow, ſpeaking thus within our ſelues: Why haue I greater care of my ſelf, then my Lord god willeth that I haue, ſeing I am not myne owne but his, who loueth me tenderly, &amp; can not but continually behould me.</p>
                  <p>May we not then ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſeke meanes to deliuer and free our ſelues
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25031:60"/>from ſuffering ſuch paynefull thinges and aduerſyties, or we ſhoulde beare them ſtill with ioy, &amp; let them alone to godds care &amp; prouidence.</p>
                  <p>As it is godds will ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that ſo long as we haue them, we euer ſuffer them with ioy, how painfull ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be, &amp; take them as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of our moſt louing father (which ioyfull patience, will greatly mitigate their paine) ſo it is alſo his will, that we procure &amp; vſe with ioyfull mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuch meanes for our remedie, &amp; deliuerance, as we know he haith left vs, and would haue vs to take, as phiſicke in ſicknes, meate in hunger, peace &amp; ſaifty in perſecution, and the lyke: But all this becauſe it is his will we doe it, and that our frailties may ſerue him the better, being deliuered from ſuch moleſtations &amp; troubles.</p>
                  <p>How ſhall we ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> dryue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way &amp; expell, theſe motions of ſorows and greiues, which the miſeries of this world bringe hourly vpon vs, &amp; how ſhall we get this ioy, whiles we are in the paines of them?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25031:60"/>
                  <p>The ſeruant of God ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> muſt be alwaies prouident and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo ſone as the paſſion of ſorow or greife beginneth to ryſe by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any aduerſitie preſently reiect and refuſe it by the acte of his will, as I toulde you in the vſe of that power, in the firſte inſtruction: Yea he muſt endeuour to moue and enforce his will to couet and embrace the things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon thoſe paines, greiues, and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, grow. For whyles theſe things be deſired the ſorow ceaſeth as it roſe at the firſt, becauſe the ſame thinges were diſlyked or hated. He ſhoulde therfore acquaint and accuſtome him ſelf, to ioy and be gladd, in all pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſorowfull thinges, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri-wyſe, to ſorow in all thinges which are ioyfull and bringe delight, as it is ſaid.
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Sorow for ioy, &amp; ioy for payne.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Kepe with thee as a certaine gayne.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> Why ſhoulde we ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> couet theſe thinges, wherby ſuch greif and moleſtation come to vs?</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:25031:61"/>
                  <p>Firſt ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 2</note> becauſe they come all from the hand of God as Iob ſaith. Again becauſe we deſerue them by our ſinnes. Laſtlye becauſe they bringe to vs many commodities, and cure the feſtred vlcers of our ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OF HOPE.</head>
                  <p>NOwe by Hope (not as it is the thirde ſupernaturall vertue, but a naturall affection or paſſion, common to all mankinde) we expecte and looke for many thinges of this life either pleaſante or commodious to vs. Yet nothing we hope for, ſhould ſettle it ſelf or take place in our hartes, but onely God, &amp; theſe thinges whereby we thinke our ſelues, to draw nearer to him &amp; ſerue him. Whatſoeuer is beſides, we ought to eſteeme it as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge. And if we perceiue the Hope of any thinge, to be more fixed in our harte, or to occupye &amp; delighte our myndes, then the bliſſe of heauen or vertues, which we hope from God: it muſte forth-withe be expelled, as a moſt hurtfull and diſordered thinge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25031:61"/>
                  <head>OF FEARE.</head>
                  <p>IN lyke manner alſo all feare is to be lefte that is not of God, as our Sauiour willed vs, not to feare them that kill the bodye, and can doe noe more: but God that can caſt both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; ſoule into hell fyre. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaid, <hi>God is the protectour of my life; whom ſhall I feare.</hi> All the moments of our lyues, with all thinges belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge vnto vs, are in the hande of god, and can not happen to vs, otherwyſe then he will permitt. And therefore we ſhould rather wiſh our owne eyes to be pulled owte, then aduiſedly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt any thinge that may diſpleaſe his Maieſty: For all other thinges, there is no cauſe why we ſhould feare them.</p>
                  <p>For thoughe all the calamities of the worlde fall vpon vs: yet if we feare them not, they can doe vs noe harm nor true euill, but rather if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them corragiouſly &amp; bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; receiue them ioyfully, becauſe it is our Lordes will we ſuffer them in memorye of thoſe he ſuffered for vs: they will increaſe in vs, eternall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25031:62"/>of glory &amp; honour.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore we ſhould be prepared alwaies to repute as nothing, or rather to eſte me as moſte preceous Iewells &amp; ornaments: all troubles &amp; moleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the world. And if at anie tyme ſome feare creepe vpon vs: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with our will, to encounter &amp; repell it, leſt it occupye the place, in which the reuerent feare of God moſt neceſſary for vs, ſhould be harbored.</p>
                  <p>He that can moderate, rule, and ſubdue, theſe paſſions in this ſorte, ſhall enioye greate peace, and arryue ſhortly, to high perfection of vertue, &amp; be able rightly to iudg of all things, as the chriſtian philoſopher <hi>Boetius</hi> ſaith.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If thou wilt the truth behoulde with light moſt cleare:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Away with Ioy, Sorow, Hope, and Feare.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>Hauinge declared, what way you may repaire the ruyne &amp; deſtruction of your ſoule: it remaineth now that we ſpeake of the loue of God, which Exerciſe is the moſt principall ſeruice
<pb facs="tcp:25031:62"/>can doe him, &amp; the ende of all which we haue ſpoken of hitherto.</p>
                  <p>Take your reſte nowe, for you are wearie with trauell: in the morninge God willing, we ſhall make an ende of this matter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>THE THIRDE PARTE. CONTEYNING the way how to loue God, our neighbours, and our ſelues.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THE LOVE OF GOD.</head>
               <p>AFter they had ſlepte a whyle, &amp; <hi>Alphonſo</hi> finiſhed his vſuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions: they came together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp; <hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:25031:63"/>
               <p>Now my ſonn, if you be ſatiſfyed in all thinges we talked of yeſter night: Let vs goe forward as I promiſed you. I reſt fully ſatiſfyed ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> in all you haue ſaid hitherto: Therefore I pray you procede to teach me how I may loue God.</p>
               <p>The loue of God ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is a fyre, which God would haue all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes burninge, on the Altar of our ſoule, &amp; if you throughlye knewe the worthines and excellency thereof, all woulde ſeeme litle, that hitherto we haue ſaid, of the reparation &amp; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſoule, by which ſo high a woorke is to be performed. For the acte of louing God is of ſo greate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, that not Sainct in heauen, nor any thinge that is or can be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can doe any woork more high or perfecte. For which cauſe the ſonn of God him ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22</note> calleth this the greateſt and firſt commaundement. Yea if all the endeuours &amp; ſtrengthes of Angells &amp; men, were heaped together in one Angell or man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he coulde do nothing more worthy, then is the acte of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:25031:63"/>God. And nothing that is or can be made, by the omnipotente power of God: can be ſufficient to loue God with that perfection which his infinite goodnes &amp; worthines doth deſerue.</p>
               <p>This loue of God, incomparably excelleth all other ſupernaturall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues or woorks, &amp; without it, none other gift or qualitye that man haith, profitethe him anythinge at all, or is to be eſtemed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13</note> as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. This is the inceſſant &amp; eternall woorke of God him ſelf: For he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of infinite goodnes &amp; excellency, is infinitely to be loued, and is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallye occupyed with all his infinite power, in lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge his owne infinite goodnes &amp; ioying in the ſame. And nothing being more conſonante to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, nothinge ſo profitable or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to our ſelues, then that we loue him, who is an infinite good, &amp; infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely to be beloued, &amp; whom we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſufficiently loue as he deſerueth, albeit our ſtrength &amp; abilityes were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinite: His moſte holy and righteous will is, that we doe the ſame thinge,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25031:64"/>with all our forces, which he dothe continually with his: that is, loue him &amp; ioy in him with all our harts, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; ſtrength. Yea &amp; ſo greatly he requyreth &amp; deſireth this moſt diuine woork of vs, that he would yeld him ſelf to a moſt cruell death, that ſo he might procure &amp; prouoke vs to loue him, &amp; all this for our good, &amp; not for any benefite of his owne.</p>
               <p>All other thinges beſides this loue of God which are commaunded vs, or in the holy ſcriptures requyred of vs, are but for that they be helpes to this loue, &amp; to omitt them, would great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the ſame. Vyces &amp; ſinnes forbidden vs, are nothing els, but a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inordinate loue of vaine things, which occupye the place of our hartes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted onely for God. Neither doe vertues ſerue for other ende, then fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſpoſe the ſoule for this loue: Which vertues notwithſtanding, are ſo neceſſarie for this loue of God, that it were great preſumption, to thinke we coulde obtein it, without great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe in them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:64"/>
               <p>To loue God ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> muſt of neceſſitie be a worke, of great excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencye and worthines: but I pray you tell me what this loue is, and how it may be done.</p>
               <p>I muſt tell you firſt ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> how there be two ſortes of loues, or louers of God. The one loueth him, for that he is a ſweete and bountifull lorde, moſt liberally communicating his goodnes to his creatures: Theſe are alſo much delighted in his ſeruice, and they aſke many giftes of him, &amp; pray with great contemplation of his Magnificency and knowledge of the excellency of vertues &amp; graces which they pray for. Often alſo they come to him, as to the fountain of all ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And by reaſon of the greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light &amp; conſolation, which they feele in their ſoule, they imagin this loue of theires to be moſt perfect &amp; of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt meritt.</p>
               <p>This ſeemeth ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> to be a perfect louer of God.</p>
               <p>I wiſhe ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that all they which loue not God: would loue him
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25031:65"/>at the leaſt in this ſorte. But the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God permitteth not his true louers to be content with this kynd of loue though it be good, &amp; may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce to exerciſe beginners &amp; nouices in for ſom time, becauſe from this they eaſely paſſe, to the higheſt &amp; moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue, whereof by &amp; by I will tell you.</p>
               <p>How may we know ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> that this kynd of loue, is imperfect &amp; fraile?</p>
               <p>They that loue in this manner ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> forth-with when this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall ſweetenes is wantinge &amp; depat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, goe with an heauy hart, and dull courage abowt thinges which belong to God. And they are ſo ouercome with the frailties of their owne nature, as almoſt if they had not had any ſuch loue at all. For they procure &amp; ſeke for corporall delights, as to eate and drinke daintely: They deſire and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept worldly fauours, frendſhipps, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures, praiſe, eſtimation, &amp; other vayne thinges, pleaſing their ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (yet without mortall ſinn) aſmuch as other perſons, that neuer had taſted
<pb facs="tcp:25031:65"/>of things perteining to god. Yea &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the very tyme when they are viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with ſuch ſwetenes: they are intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with certain vaine affections, &amp; ſuch as be ſomtimes not a litle ſenſuall, as delighted with the ſweete natures, conditions, familiarities, &amp; bewtie, of ſome perſons. Againe, theſe louers commonly couet to be ſeene and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted deuout, and they are greued when they perceiue, they are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for ſuch, neither doe they ioy when they perceiue other perſons to be reckned more deuout &amp; better qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified then them ſelues. Theſe &amp; ſuch like ſports &amp; imperfections they haue: All which be ſo abiect, that the high loue of God (which we are to ſpeake of) doth not brooke them with it, no not when it wantethe that ſweetenes in the ſenſuall appetites: whereby we may rightlye conclude, this kynde of louer, to be frayle &amp; imperfect, as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cheefely for his owne commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or delight.</p>
               <p>If this loue will not ſerue: to what purpoſe is it ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:25031:66"/>
               <p>It is verye profitable ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> firſt, becauſe he that haith it, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely caſt from him the forſaid imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and ſpottes, with the loue of vaine thinges.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe ſuch a louer, is in a verieneare diſpoſition, to produce many actes of the higheſte and moſt perfect loue, when he knoweth it.</p>
               <p>Which is then this ſecond kynde of loue ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſaid <hi>Alphonſo, A certayne acte or woork of our will, veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly (&amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes alſo with ſweetenes) louing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyring, that God be that infiuite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he is:</hi> And poſſeſſe aſmuch glory, dominion, &amp; power, as indede he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth to him ſelf, ouer vs &amp; all things. And again, that whatſoeuer is or may be, loue him, ſerue him, and glorify him, for his infinite goodnes &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines onely. And all this is done for that the excellency of his Maieſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth that we doe it, with all oure abilitie &amp; ſtrengthe.</p>
               <p>He therfore that would truly and perfectly loue God, muſt often me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
<pb facs="tcp:25031:66"/>&amp; call to mynde what God is, &amp; delight in him. Moreouer thinke what great glory he haith, and what dominion ouer vs &amp; all creatures, &amp; ioye for it, as men are wonte to ioye for the dignitye &amp; dominion of their deareſt frends. And with this alſo be muſt wiſh, that all thinges may ſerue &amp; loue him, deſiring this a thowſand wayes, &amp; procuring it ten thowſand, &amp; all this for God &amp; his goodnes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. For it is meete &amp; iuſte, that we loue his infinite goodnes &amp; power, in moſt excellente manner that may be deuiſed. And ſeinge noe ende is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then God him ſelf, who is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge &amp; ende of all thinges; it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowethe, that he oughte to be loued principally, not for that which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or hope for of him, but for him ſelf which is infinitly amiable.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we ſhoulde accuſtome our willes, that they be moued to loue &amp; to be delighted, in the perfection, glorie, &amp; treaſures of our Lorde, not becauſe we feele ſwetenes in this loue nor for the giftes we haue receiued or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25031:67"/>hope to receiue hereafter, but forgea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as it were theſe thinges, loue him as moſte worthy to haue all the willes &amp; powers of Angells &amp; men occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in deſiring &amp; delightinge that his Maieſtye haue all the infinite good it haith without reſpecte that any parte thereof, may redownd to vs, though indeede ſo much the more ſhall com to vs, by how muche more we loue him without reſpect of our own good.</p>
               <p>By what certaine marke or ſigne ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> may we knowe, when a man haith this loue?</p>
               <p>He haith it ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth god aſmuche when he ſheweth him ſelf ſeuere &amp; ſharpe, as when he is ſweete &amp; my Ide; aſmuche when by iuſtice he puniſheth, as when merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he geueth benefites: aſmuch in aduerſitie as proſperity. Such a man loueth not God becauſe he is dulce &amp; ſweete: Yet he loueth ſweetenes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is geuen by God, &amp; bringeth him courage to ſerue God more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently: He is not terrifyed nor affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with chaſtiſments, but taketh them
<pb facs="tcp:25031:67"/>with that loue which the holy hande &amp; fatherly will of God that ſcourgeth doth requyre. He praiethe not, as drawne with loue &amp; ſweetenes of the gift, but that his ſoule enryched ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, may waxe ſtronger &amp; more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent in godds ſeruice. He is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended or troubled to ſee him ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate of conſolations, yet he ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth if any thing be in him which haith diſpleaſed or doth offende, the eyes of ſo high a Maieſtie. He aſketh not forgeuenes &amp; pardon of his ſinnes for eſcapinge paine, or recouering his loſt grace, vertues, tytle, &amp; right to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall gloue, but that his ſoule (hauing obteyned pardon) may be more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; acceptable to God, &amp; may loue &amp; ſerue his highnes in puritie.</p>
               <p>He haith noe affection, that may withdraw his hart any other way from God. He doth not remember or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, whether men think of him or noe. He is not greeued, when he is contemned or reiected. He ſhunneth &amp; is ſorowfull for creditt &amp; honoure offered him, fearing leſt they be vnto
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25031:68"/>him, hinderances to humilitye. He ioyeth for the good &amp; honoure of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thinking that they accept or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them, without ambition or vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for the better ſeruice of God and helpe of his people. Such a louer haith all thinges, and yet haith nothing.</p>
               <p>He ſubmitteth him ſelf to all, &amp; all ſerue him. He ſhunneth all ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and he feelethe nothing but that is ſweete. In God whom he loueth, he knoweth what he oughte to doe, to ſpeake, to thinke: &amp; for him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he thinketh, he ſpeaketh, he doth euery thinge. He liuinge, is not he that liueth, but it is Chriſt that hueth in him, geuinge him to liue a diuine lyſe. In louing him ſelf, he louethe not him ſelf, but he louethe God all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, for whoſe ſake he deſirethe all good thinges. He ioyethe in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge, but that whereby his Lorde is ſerued, &amp; that he thinketh gratefull in his ſighte. And finallye, he euer ioyeth in his hart and thanketh God who in louinge him ſelf infinitly, doth ſupply what is due to him from all his
<pb facs="tcp:25031:68"/>creatures.</p>
               <p>How may we gett this loue of god ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is vaine preſumption ſaid <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> for any man to thinke, he can leap to it at his pleaſure, withowt making due preparation, &amp; folowing the ſame pathe which godds ſonn haith made vs both by his owne example &amp; docrrine.</p>
               <p>What preparation or pathes are theſe ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that would receiue this pretious liquour into his ſoule ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> muſt firſte of neceſſitye occupye him ſelf for many daies in theſe Exercyſes which I tould you of in the ſeconde parte, but before all, in the holie ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of him ſelf: otherwyſe he ſhall be deceiued &amp; profitt nothing at all.</p>
               <p>I vnderſtand you well ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That done ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> he muſt woork diligently in this ſorte, whether he be preuented by God with bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of ſweetnes or not. He muſt breefly call to minde, how vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; infinite the good &amp; glorie is that God poſſeſſeth, conſidering him
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25031:69"/>as the beſt and moſt worthy, that all creatures ioy for his goodnes, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon by &amp; by inclyne his will to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, &amp; ioy for ſo great a good of his Lord, &amp; let him continew in that act ſo long as he can. If he be a litle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted or waxe could in it, let him forth-with retorne to it againe in the ſame manner, his hart euer leapinge with ioy, in conſideringe God to be full of infinite perfections &amp; goodnes, And by continuance, he ſhall doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be aduaunced to this perfect loue.</p>
               <p>The honour, glorie, &amp; perfections of our Lord are infinite &amp; of infinite excellency, and in lyke ſorte, euerye thinge in particuler that he woorketh or createth, doth ſhew forth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to vs, a ſingular goodnes &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines in him. And ſeing that all the moments of our lyfe, ſuffice not fully to heare, or conſider them as they are in him: we ought at the leaſt, vnder name &amp; tytle of infinite goodnes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; perfections, to heape them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; to produce actes of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that God haue them all, and to
<pb facs="tcp:25031:69"/>ioy all the minutes of our lyfe that he haith them conſidering we owe all this to him as moſt due. And ſo muche may we exercyſe our ſelues in theſe actes (although we want that ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which they call deuotion) that in euery place &amp; buſines, we may oft loue God in this ſorte, withowte ſeking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſolitary places, as it hapneth daily when one frend ioyeth ſodanly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owt more opportunitie of place or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye, when he heareth or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth ſome good to haue befallen his deare frende. That which I toulde you before of the vſe of your will, &amp; of the ende of all your actions, helpe much in theſe actes how you ſhoulde produce them, &amp; that you muſt doe all for this ende, becauſe God is moſt worthy of it, &amp; deſireth that we doe it for him.</p>
               <p>Perhapps ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> we might gett this loue more eaſilye by prayer, doinge as you taughte me, when you ſpake of it, &amp; by the exercyſes of thoſe vertues you reherſed before.</p>
               <p>He ſhall obteyne it ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:25031:70"/>the ſoner &amp; better, that together with praier, will help him ſelf with the acts of his will, as I toulde you before: which he may doe both in prayer and without it. For in euery ſuch act, there is a new ſeruice to God, &amp; a new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the loue of God, of grace, &amp; of meritt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="✿"/> And as noe artificer, how ſkilfull ſoeuer he be, profiteth any thing by his arte, but onely whyles he woorketh in it, ſo the ſeruant of God, is made rycher in the loue of God, but onely when he produce the ſpeciall actes of the ſame loue: Which acte of loue, how ſhort ſoeuer it be, beinge a farr greater, better, more preceous, and a more ineſtimable good, then all thinges els that any creature can doe in heauen or earth: We ought euery houre many tymes to worke it, that doinge our beſt endeuour in it during this lyfe, we may receiue more grace and ability to worke it for euer in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where thoſe bleſſed Saincts loue God more feruently &amp; more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which more loued him heare on earth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:70"/>
               <p>Wherfore we ſhould deepely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and condemne our owne negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and folly: and ſeinge we ought neuer to ceaſe from this acte of louing god (both becauſe it is dew to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and the acte of it ſelf is of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable profit) we ſhould moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly lament euery moment of our life that we lett paſſe without this loue.</p>
               <p>And ſpecially we ought to bewaile our ſinnes, which (if they be mortall) are deadlye enemies to it, or (if they be veniall) hinder ſo great a good, and coole the feruour thereof. In like ſorte alſo ſhould we reproue ourſelues if we be not exceding glad and ioyfull, of euery thing that may further vs to it as iniuries, contempts, perſecutions, &amp;c. Or if we ſorow not ſo much whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie impediment is geuen vs to it, as are humaine fauour, ſenſuall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane delectation, temporall honours, credit, prayſes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Out frailty is ſuch ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> &amp; our neceſſitie ſo great, that oftentimes we can not be gladd of iniuries, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, and the lyke, nor refuſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25031:71"/>thinges delectable and proſperous.</p>
               <p>It ſomtimes ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> through weaknes of body, or becauſe as yet we haue not gotten ſo muche vertue as were nedefull for our ſufferinge of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities ioyfully, but we muſt flee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and our perſecutoures, or againe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and receiue delicate and pleaſant thinges: In ſuch caſes I ſay, we muſte looke that we doe theſe thinges with actuall intention for auoyding greater euills, and ſorow alſo much, in that by fleing aduerſities and troubles, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from a thing which ſhould further vs to ſo great a good as is the loue of God. And againe that by takinge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable thinges, we omitt and forgo the ſharpe, which are moſt due vnto vs for puniſhment of our ſinnes &amp; negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
               <p>All this moreouer we ought to doe with humble prayer to our Lord, that he would vouchſaife to ſtrengthen vs in body and ſoule, for better reſiſtinge oure owne frailtie, whereby through defect of our vertue, it is needefull we auoyde ſuch trouble, or vſe ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull
<pb facs="tcp:25031:71"/>thinges, and that alſo by his grace, we may be diſpoſed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe impediments of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, perfectly to loue him.</p>
               <p>What remedye &amp; helpe haue we ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> if we finde our ſelues ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie dull &amp; heauy, whiles we endeuour to produce theſe actes of loue, &amp; to bring all our motions, into the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience &amp; ſeruice of God: for ſo it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hapneth in other exercyſes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion &amp; well doinge.</p>
               <p>The ſame may happen alſo in this high woork ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but then we may aſſure our ſelues that it cometh becauſe we wante the holy hatred of our ſelues, which is the foundation &amp; moſt principall diſpoſition to this loue of God. Or again, becauſe there cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in our hartes ſome inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to ſome earthly thinge, as loue of neede leſſe delectation, or affection to ſome perſon or buſines not rightly ordered. Wherefore he that feleth him ſelf ſo dull, muſt ſearch owt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently in him ſelf, ſuch defect or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and take it away by contrary
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25031:72"/>actes, as we taughte before, and ſhall more hereafter.</p>
               <p>For to inclyne our will to produce actes of the loue of God, aboue all thinges, withowt hauinge firſt gotten the holy hatred of our ſelues, or whiles our affection to any earthly thing that may deilght vs endureth (not being ordeyned or referred either actuallye or virtually to God) is much lyke as if a man would cutt with a hammer, thinges requiringe a raiſoure or ſharpe knyfe. For the perfection &amp; excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this loue (the leaſt act wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may aduance a man to a highe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of eternall glory in heauen) doth not permitt with it, any ſuch vyle &amp; baiſe thinge. Beſides this alſo the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, muſt be warie of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of his mortall enemy the deuil, who neuer ceaſeth to moleſt and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them that goe forwarde in any ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but moſte maliceouſly goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt to harme and ouerthrow them, that endeuour to obteyne, this moſt holy loue of God.</p>
               <p>What way I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25031:72"/>can he cheefly hinder vs?</p>
               <p>Among many other ſaid <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> he hindrethe vs by one, which is verie ſecrett, &amp; yet much daungerous &amp; hurtfull, that is, by a certain meane eſtimation, contempt, negligence, &amp; couldnes of the minde, towardes the woork of the loue of God, which ſome perſons haue, whiles they think, heare, or reade, the cheife poynt of it to conſiſte, in the deſyre of Godds perfections, goodnes, &amp; glorie, &amp; in ioying in them as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>How can this ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> happen to any man in this holy woork?</p>
               <p>It hapneth ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> becauſe they litle conceiue or marke the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of this thing, &amp; the enemy doth aſſaile &amp; trouble them withall: And principally it chanceth to them that are not preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with the ſwetenes which this loue is accuſtomed to bringe with it.</p>
               <p>For they hearing as I ſaid euen now this loue to conſiſt in this, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire &amp; inwardly feele in our ſelues, a complacency &amp; ioy, for all the infinit
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25031:73"/>goodnes and glory which are in god: &amp; this onely for God: they wax could, thinking this worke not to be ſo high &amp; excellent as it is, but iudge other woorkes aſwell corporall as ſpirituall, to excede this, &amp; to be more beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming godds ſeruantes, as preachinge, diſputing gouerninge others, feigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the faith, almes deedes, faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, afflictions, and the lyke.</p>
               <p>Whereupon ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> commeth this falſe conceipt of theirs?</p>
               <p>It commeth ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> firſte by reaſon the deuill tempteth them, and withall, the taiſt and appetite of their ſoule, is diſtempered and corrupted, as I toulde you yeſter nighte, in the fourth inſtruction, by the example of the ſick man, that by reaſon of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected taiſt, deſireth hurtfull meates, and taketh loath with wholeſom.</p>
               <p>What remedie haue we againſt this noyſom impediment ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt prouyde firſt ſaid <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> that our corrupt appetite be cured, as I ſaid in the fourth inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which done, they that feele this couldnes, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25031:73"/>haue this wrong eſtimation, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent perceiue, all other workes, how worthy &amp; meruelous ſoeuer they ſeme, to be verie abiect &amp; baſe,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi>
                  </note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of this loue, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs. And our <hi>Saui ur</hi> him ſelf, beinge the eternall wiſdom of God, (which can not erre or deceiue vs) haith choſen &amp; commaunded the ſame aboue all thinges which may be done in heauen or earth. A reaſon hereof you may haue alſo, if you conſider that albeit our free will &amp; the actes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (which I toulde you before in the fourth inſtruction, to be of greateſte dignitie in vs) be of them ſelues, litle worth or of ſmall commoditie: Yet may we make them of ineſtimable dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie &amp; valew, if we vnite our will &amp; moſt ſtrongly faſten it, to the will of God, which is of an infinite excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in ſuch manner ioyning ours vnto his, that it be not carried to any other thinge, but what his bleſſed will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth. For then the acte &amp; deſire of our infirme &amp; baſe free will, groweth to be of infinite valewe and dignitie,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25031:74"/>when (forſaking our ſelues) we take the deſire of that infinite will which is God, who inceſſantly willeth, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, &amp; ioyeth, for the infinite good &amp; worthines he haith.</p>
               <p>Why requyreth God ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> that we ſhoulde deſire loue &amp; ioye in this ſort: as he euer doth?</p>
               <p>He would haue vs doe it ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phouſo,</hi> firſt for that his loue &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to vs, would haue our abiect free will, aduaunced to ſo greate nobilitie &amp; honour, as to haue an act of infinite and diuine valew. Againe, becauſe (ſeing he haith created vs to ſo great a good as to enioy him ſelf) it is iuſte that we yelde him this ſeruice at leaſt as to occupye our ſelues all the tyme of our mortall lyfe, in louing him and ioying for his good &amp; glorye, as we ſee faithfull ſeruantes &amp; louinge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to reioyce, for the goodes &amp; honour their Lordes gett. Thirdlye, that heare on earth we may occupye our ſelues, &amp; begin that worke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our eternall glory and beatitude in heauen, cheifly muſt conſiſt. For gods
<pb facs="tcp:25031:74"/>holye Sainctes, clearlye behouldinge his nature &amp; eſſence, are repleniſhed with an infinite knowledge, to iudge what goodnes &amp; glorye his Maieſtie is worthy of: &amp; alſo with an infinite deſire and loue, that he poſſeſſe the ſame. Which burning deſire &amp; loue of theirs, when (behouldinge God) they ſee it fulfilled in more perfecte ſorte then they can wiſhe, imagine, or comprehende, they are rauiſhed with vnſpeakable ioyes &amp; gladnes.</p>
               <p>The happye Sainctes in heauen, haue the manifeſt viſion &amp; perfect fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of all his goodnes, &amp; therefore their knowledg, loue, &amp; ioy, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. We ſinfull wormes on earthe by the lighte of our catholicke faith (though obſcurelye, yet moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlye &amp; firmlye) beleue the ſame, which they behoulde. And therefore God will, that we occupy our powers as much as we can, in the ſame loue, deſire &amp; ioy, of the infinite goodnes &amp; glory of our Lorde. For the more we loue him, &amp; ioye in his goodnes here on earth: the more perfecte and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:25031:75"/>greater, ſhall oure loue &amp; ioyes be in heauen.</p>
               <p>I conceiue all this ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> but many without doubt, haue obteyned the perfecte loue of God requyred in this lyfe, withoute all this adoe, or knowledg of this way you haue taught me.</p>
               <p>Many haue indeede ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> loued God perfectly, before this way was either known to me, or taught in this manner, by any that I haue hard: but ſurely the ordinary way to get it, haith bene this in ſubſtance. For it is gathered owt of the holy Scriptures, accordinge to the declaration of the holye Doctoures, which haue writen of this matter.</p>
               <p>Many haue thought &amp; thinke ſtill that they haue gotten it verie eaſelye withowt theſe reaſons &amp; meanes, but comonly they fayled of it, &amp; gott but the weake &amp; imperfecte loue which I ſpake of before.</p>
               <p>If you thinke good we will now paſſe to the loue of oure neighbours.</p>
               <p>Doe ſo I pray you ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:75"/>
               <head>OF THE LOVE OF OVR Neighboure.</head>
               <p>AS the loue of God ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> requyred before it, all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſes and conſiderations we ſpake of: ſo the loue of our neighbour &amp; of our ſelues, requyred before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of god. For it is neceſſary that theſe two loues procede from the loue of god, otherwyſe they can not be good or well ordered. You muſte know then that he which deſireth to ſerue &amp; pleaſe God: muſt mark and obſerue two things. The firſt is, what God would haue him to doe: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde, in what manner he would haue it done. For he ſhoulde haue ſmall thanke, or rewarde with God, that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld doe his commaundemente, if he did it not in the manner he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it. He haith bidden vs to loue one an other ſaying, <hi>This is my precept, that you loue one an other:</hi> and with this, in what ſorte alſo we ſhould doe it ſayinge, <hi>as I haue loued you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He then that doth the firſte, ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25031:76"/>not haue the high reward due to that loue, except alſo he doe the ſeconde.</p>
               <p>Now therefore to knowe how we ought one to loue an other; we muſt conſider how our Lord loued vs.</p>
               <p>Firſt by many waies &amp; meanes, he drew &amp; induced vs to the loue of god: Then he taught vs by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to ſuffer patiently, all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of this world, neuer ſacking the raynes to vain delights, aboue that which might be neceſſary to the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation of his body. Then he dyed for vs, that we mighte haue thereby vertues, grace, &amp; glorye. In this kind of loue he meruelouſly exceeded, &amp; was a moſt vehemente enemye to all vayne loue which now paſſeth among vs, &amp; is ordinarily verie corrupt &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecticus to our ſoules, created to be the temples of God. Accordinge to this example therefore of our Lorde, we ought to frame our Loue towardes our neighboures, caſtinge away all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, which are accuſtomed to mixe them ſelues with our loue, as to be much affected to ſome perſons, for that
<pb facs="tcp:25031:76"/>we ſee them vertuous &amp; deuout, and in their conuerſat on, to be mylde, graccous, &amp; amiable: In the loue of whom often good menns hartes, are taken captyue, finding greife, diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes &amp; trouble of mynde, to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, or not to talke with them or not to be mutually beloued &amp; eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of them: All which kinde of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection &amp; loue is vaine and hurtfull to the ſeruantes of God.</p>
               <p>Me think ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> we mighte well loue others in this forte, becauſe we ſee them goddes ſeruants, cheifly if we doe it for God.</p>
               <p>If your frend ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> had a ſeruant, the loue of whom, ſhoulde ſo hould captiue your hart, &amp; ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe, that it more delighted you, to conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe and talke with him, then with your frende: were it not manifeſt that now you loue not the ſeruant for your frende, but becauſe his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation &amp; nature is ſweete &amp; gratefull to you. For though your loue towards that ſeruant, beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n for your frendes ſake, yet now it is become inordinate
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:25031:77"/>and exceſſiue &amp; more for your owne pleaſure &amp; delight you take in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, then wholly for reſpect of your frend: Euen thus we may ſpeake of that loue you rehearſed. It is playne mockerie to ſay it is loue of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour purely for god, notwithſtanding there be perhaps ſome part of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue therewith. But he that is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; wholly addicted to God, taketh noe parte from him, but geuethe him all, occupying &amp; beſtowing his wholl affection on him, or in ſome thinge, that is wholly ordered or directed to him, as ſuch vaine loue can not be, beinge more for ſome thing in a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, then for God.</p>
               <p>Our loue ſhould be towardes all the ſeruants of our Father, aſwell our enemies as frendes, with ſo great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as may proceede, from the loue we haue to him, that all other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſett aſyde, onelye that may haue place which we owe vnto God.</p>
               <p>To auoyde &amp; caſte of all which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſiuous affections, thoſe things may help, which I toulde you of before,
<pb facs="tcp:25031:77"/>ſpeakinge of the naturall affection of ioy, &amp; of the vſe of our will.</p>
               <p>How then ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> ſhoulde we loue our neighboures?</p>
               <p>Our loue to them, ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> ſhoulde ſpringe altogether from the loue of God, that (conſidering they are ſo highly beloued of him, that he would yeld him ſelf to death for them when yet they were his enemies) we ſhoulde loue them all ſo much, as to help them in all that is good &amp; nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for their bodies &amp; ſoules, lyke as we are wonte loue them that muche delight vs: Yea &amp; this we ſhould do, though their conuerſation weare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtfull &amp; odious vnto vs, entreatinge them curteouſly, &amp; prouiding for their neceſſities, as for them which are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly beloued of our heauenly Lorde &amp; Father, who willeth &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs ſo to doe. All this we ought to doe, with as ſeruent a will as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for gratifying, pleaſinge, &amp; obeyinge our Lorde, how iniurious &amp; noyſome ſoeuer they be vnto vs.</p>
               <p>It is verie harde ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25031:78"/>beare ſuch tender affection to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as we may doe to our frends &amp; benefactoures.</p>
               <p>Our corrupt natures ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> finde difficultie to loue our enemies, but the children of God muſt not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure nor order their actions, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination &amp; motions of their corrupte affections, but by the rule of gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will and commaundement. And a reſolute will of ſeruing God, maketh them noe leſſe firme &amp; conſtante in louing him, whom their owne inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections would hate, then him whom by the aboundance of benefites &amp; good turnes, they are inclyned to loue.</p>
               <p>Yet with all this you muſte know, that albeit our loue ought to be in this ſort equally to euery one: yet ought we firſt to ſhew it in good effects and benefites, towards them that are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, &amp; them we are behoulden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. For godds will is, that our chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rly diſpoſed, preferringe in theſe good benefites, euery one, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we are diuerſly bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:25031:78"/>them.</p>
               <p>God haith alſo ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to loue our neighboures, as we loue our ſelues, which is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of louinge them, then as our Sauiour loued vs.</p>
               <p>He haith commaunded ſo indeede ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> but this manner &amp; the other, are all one in effect &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if they be rightly vnderſtoode. For the loue which we ſhoulde haue to our ſelues, ought to be the ſame, and in the ſame manner, as our Sauioure loued vs. We will therefore if it pleaſe you goe forward, &amp; declare in what ſort we are to loue our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Doe ſo I ptay you ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for it can not but be a pleaſant hearinge, &amp; without all perill of offending any, euery one being deſireous, to loue him ſelf as much as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:25031:79"/>
               <head>OF THE LOVE OF OVR SELVES.</head>
               <p>OVr naturall inclination ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> to the loue of our ſelues, is ſo great &amp; vehemente, that God haith not geuen vs any commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement thereof, yet by the blyndnes &amp; corruption of ſinn, we haue in moſt part loſt our iudgment &amp; knowledge, how we ought to doe it.</p>
               <p>He therefore that would truly loue himſelf, muſt obſerue three thinges.</p>
               <p>Firſt that by all meanes he procure any thinge wheareby he knoweth any good may come to him ſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly that he flee and auoyde, whatſoeuer may bring him damage or euill.</p>
               <p>Thirdly that he refuſe not to offer &amp; yelde him ſelf to any difficulties for obteyninge his owne good.</p>
               <p>Our naturall reaſon and the lighte of our Catholick faith, ſufficientlye teach vs, which be true goodes &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills, &amp; which be apparent &amp; deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And we muſt be verey circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:25031:79"/>&amp; diligent that we erre not, in diſcerning theſe, or folow not the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable inclinations &amp; appetites of our owne ſenſualitie, takinge that for good, which indeede is hurtfull, or fleeing that as euill, which in truthe is our good.</p>
               <p>Now he that would enrich him ſelf with good thinges, muſt know, that in euery good he deſirethe, or may obteyne, two thinges are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. One is, the good that may come to himſelf, by that thing. The other is, that it is godds will &amp; deſire, that he haue that thing. Of theſe two he ought litle or noe whitt, to eſteme the benefite or good that may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him ſelf of the thing he deſireth or doth as it is his owne: In reſpecte of the ſeconde; that it is the ſeruice of God, &amp; the fulfilling of his holy will as I toulde you before in the fifth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, ſpeaking of the end of all our actions &amp; deſires.</p>
               <p>Our Lord haith geuen vs a prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ornament or Iewell, where-with we may excedingly enriche our ſelues
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25031:80"/>at any tyme, that is our appetite and will, the which we (as it were) gilde with coper or tinne, when we deſyre &amp; loue anything for our owne good &amp; benefite: And againe, we adorne &amp; bewtify it with diuyne goulde, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (forgeating our ſelues) we deſire and loue any good thing, onely for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; ſeruinge our Lorde, &amp; fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his will. For the more we for geat ourſelues, &amp; haue care of godds ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glorie, the more care haithe God ouer vs agiane to enriche vs with all goodnes. Wherefore he that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually loueth him ſelf, muſt euer (as worldly men doe) ſtudy how to make better, all his goodes &amp; ſubſtance whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knoweth the way how it may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done. What more is to be ſaid of this poynt, I referr you to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the hatred of our ſelues.</p>
               <p>For the ſeconde alſo, which is the fleeing of all euill: I nede to ſay noe more, but he that truly loueth him ſelf muſt eſte me nothing euill or hurtfull to him, &amp; ſo flee it, but onely f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne &amp; the occaſions thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:80"/>
               <p>Now for the thirde, which is to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelf to any difficultie or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for getting his own good: I muſt admoniſh him diligently to exercyſe himſelf in the thinges that I haue ſaid before, but principally, in the hatred of him ſelf, in humilitie, in patience, and in the foure naturall affections or paſſions of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>Is there then no more neceſſary ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> for obteyninge this true loue of our ſelues?</p>
               <p>One thinge more ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is to be obſerued and practiſed diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that is. It hapneth dailye, that we doe or ſay ſomthing, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe then we ſhould haue done or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh vs, for which they that ſee or heare, (knowing our defect or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) may think the worſe of vs, &amp; the leſſe eſteme vs. In which caſe we muſt conſider, firſt the confuſion that foloweth vs thereby. In this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we muſt not comfort or animate our ſelues, in thinking that others per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps regarded not what we did or ſaid, or that perhaps they haue forgotten it,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25031:81"/>or that it ſhould not trouble vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe other men fall often into the like defects: This I ſay we ſhould not doe, but with great loue embrace that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, &amp; think that others marked vs verie well, &amp; account worſe of vs, &amp; worthily contemne vs as vnprofitable &amp; vnperfect men. For in doing thus, we make a vehement acte of patience and humilitie, and ſhortlye produce, moſt excellent habitts of them, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, doe great ſeruice to God, if we referr it to him.</p>
               <p>The other thing we are to conſider in ſuch caſes, is the euill example we geue thereby, and the diſhonoure or leſſe glory to God. For this therefore the ſeruant of God, muſt produce an acte of ſorow, for that he haith bene by that ſpeach or fact, perhaps ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of euill, or leſſe ſeruiceable to his Lorde, then he might or ſhoulde haue bene, and thus ſhall he reape co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity both on the one, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>This is all I haue to ſay of the loue of our ſelues, vnleſſe you be vnſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:25031:81"/>in ſome thing.</p>
               <p>I am verie well ſatiſſyed in all you haue ſpoken ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> &amp; I vetelye thinke, that whoſoeuer would frame him ſelf to ſerue God in this ſorte you haue toulde me, ſhould not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe excedinglye his owne meritt &amp; glory in heauen: but moreouer leade a moſt ioyfull &amp; ſweete lyfe in earth.</p>
               <p>He ſhould noe doubt finde much comfort, ioye, &amp; ſweetenes ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> ſeruing God in this ſorte, but he muſte beware, he reſte not in this ſweetenes, nor ſerue God for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God geueth it not for that ende, but that by it we may come to take delight &amp; ioye, in the conſideration of that good, glorye, &amp; dominion, which God poſſeſſeth, and that with great courage, we laude &amp; prayſe him.</p>
               <p>What is our prayſing of God ſaid <hi>Probus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All prayſe of God ſaid <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> is none other thing in vs, then a iove that we haue, to manifeſte and make knowne to all perſons, the wonderfull woorkes &amp; ineſtimable goodnes of our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25031:82"/>Lorde, in whom his ſeruants ought to delight &amp; ioye, as worldly men doe, when they heare their deare frendes, or them ſelues praiſed.</p>
               <p>Now let vs ende with thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to God for his giftes and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
               <p>Tell me this alſo ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> how ſhall I geue thankes to God?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>OF THANKES GEVING.</head>
               <p>THankſgeuing to God, ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> is nothing els but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall acte of the ſoule, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he that haith receiued a gift or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite from God, firſt recogniſeth him to be an infinite God &amp; Lorde, from whom floweth all good in heauen &amp; earth, and then ioyeth, not becauſe he is more enryched thereby, but for the glory &amp; goodnes of his Lord, and for that he ſeeth him ſelf by that gifte, more abled to loue &amp; ſerue him.</p>
               <p>Is there nothinge beſides this ſaid <hi>Probus,</hi> neceſſary in yeldinge thankes to God?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:82"/>
               <p>Beſides theſe actes of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding &amp; will ſaid <hi>Alphouſo,</hi> godds ſeruant ought vpon receipt of any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, to offer vnto God all he is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſinge &amp; annihilating him ſelf in his owne conceipt &amp; will, that ſo he may wholly in body &amp; ſoule, be deuoted into godds ſeruice, producing at that tyme greate actes of ioye, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power &amp; goodnes of god, from which that benefite came. For he that would be accounted gratefull, ought to requyte his benefactour with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinge of as great or greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew &amp; worth, then that was, which he receiued of him before.</p>
               <p>And ſeing we haue receiued of god all we haue: whatſoeuer we yelde to his ſeruice, is verie ſmall to requyte, yea, the leaſte of his benefites. We ought therefore at the leaſt, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him thanks for them, in the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I haue ſaid, &amp; this with as much loue and force, as poſſibly we may.</p>
               <p>And not onely to doe this, for the benefites beſtowed on our ſelues, but alſo for the giftes &amp; graces geuen to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25031:83"/>all his Saincts, to our frendes, to our enemies, and all his creatures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; earthe. For in ſo doinge, we make (in a ſtraunge and meruelous ſorte) the goodes of all godds crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, our owne, &amp; without regarde of our owne commoditie, we excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly increaſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now is it tyme, you were traueling. I will bring you into your way againe.</p>
               <p>I thank you Father ſaid <hi>Probus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And beinge come to the way, they embraced eche other and departed, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> to his ſolitary cell, &amp; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> towarde Ieruſalem.</p>
               <closer>Deo gratias.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:83"/>
            <head>A Table of the contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>How the Pilgrim &amp; the Ermitt mett. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>fol</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To what ende God created man.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two manners of ſeruing God.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the ruyne &amp; destruction of mans ſoule &amp; body by ſinne.</hi> 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>By what powers of our foule we may repayre our ruvne, &amp; how to vſe our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; will.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The vſe of our will.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What ende and intention we ſhoulde haue in all our actions.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How to plant good habits, &amp; extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the euill.</hi> 21</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>THE ſeconde parte.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>How to purge our ſoule from ſinn.</hi> 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hatred of our ſelues.</hi> 27</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Prayer.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Humilitye.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>HoW to ouercome the vyce of vayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorye.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Patience.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the foure naturall paſſions of the ſoule</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:25031:84"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Sorow.</hi> 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Hope.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Feare.</hi> 52</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Thirde parte.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the loue of God.</hi> 53</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the loue of our Neighbour.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the loue of our ſelues.</hi> 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Thankes geuinge.</hi> 72</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:25031:84"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the printing</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 9 <hi>pag.</hi> 1 <hi>lin.</hi> 4 <hi>Helped. reade, euer helped.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 14 <hi>pag.</hi> 2 <hi>lin.</hi> 2 <hi>greife, reade, ſorow &amp; greife.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 16 <hi>pag.</hi> 1 <hi>lin.</hi> 11 <hi>For god. reade for none other ende but onely for,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 34 <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>lin.</hi> 27 <hi>vnfeaned, reade, ready &amp; vnfeaned.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 42 <hi>pag.</hi> 1 <hi>lin.</hi> 6 <hi>hate, reade bate &amp; refuſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 52 <hi>pag.</hi> 1 <hi>lin.</hi> 7 <hi>God is, reade our Lorde is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 94 <hi>pag.</hi> 2 <hi>lin.</hi> 20 <hi>good &amp; glorye, reade, infinite good.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
